Richard, I'm I'm curious. Where are we
at the moment with RSI
>> in various weak forms? We already have
RSI. We're not quite there yet, but
we're very close.
>> When do you believe we reach ASI?
>> I think we'll take us probably several
decades.
>> On Terminal Bench 4.0, Sonnet 5.5 jumped
from 10% to 70%. Pretty extraordinary.
My theory would be that they're trying
to compete with, you know, China, which
is about three months behind, and fill
that gap before a lot of enterprises go
to to open source models.
>> It's not at all obvious to me why anyone
should be using Sonnet 5.5 over Opus 5.5
unless you have some token or latency or
other consideration. I do not plan to
use Sonnet 5.5.
>> The Defense Secretary announced Project
Meridian. It's a new Pentagon effort on
the future of warfare. It's co-led by
Elon Musk and Palmer Lucky.
>> This I think is a transformative moment.
This is a major major step forward. The
big question is going to be.
>> Now that's a moonshot. Ladies and
gentlemen,
>> this episode is brought to you by the
Abundance Summit and Link Ventures.
>> Welcome to Moonshots, everyone. Your
number one podcast and help you
understand the singularity. What's going
on? What does it mean to you and your
family and what the breaking news is? We
publish this twice a week to help you
keep up with the extraordinary rate of
change. With me today is the Fantastic
Four, Alex Weer Gross, our in-house ASI,
Dave Blendon, our improario of AI
investing, Salem Ismael, our Globe
Troder who's home today. Amazing Sem.
>> Woohoo.
>> And the and the father of the
organizational singularity. I'm Peter
Diamandis, your host and datadriven
optimist. Our mission here, keep you
optimistic about the future. Uh, and
here's the numbers from this week. In 7
days, Google shipped Gemini for Argon.
Anthropic shipped Sonnet 5.5. Open eye
shipped GPT 6.1.
Saul and the Frontier Intelligence has
gotten cheaper by three-fold. SpaceX
launched the next batch of astronauts,
the ISS, and also launched Google's TPUs
into orbit for Project Suncatcher. Uh,
if you're new to the Moonshots podcast,
please hit subscribe. We publish twice a
week and you don't want to miss any of
this news during this hypersonic
tsunami. Our moonshot here is to 20x our
subscriber base to get to 10 million to
help spread the word of optimism and the
extraordinary future that we're
building. Today on Moonshot, we're
joined by one of the architects of
modern AI, Richard. Uh, born in Germany
and trained at Stanford. Richard is
among the world's most cited natural
language processing researchers, a
pioneer in deep learning and prompt
engineering and a serial founder who's
repeatedly turned frontier research into
category defining companies. First, he
founded Metammind uh which was acquired
by Salesforce where he then became the
chief scientist leading AI research for
friend of the pod Mark Beni off. Next,
Richard founded you.com, recognized by
Time in the World Economic Forum and now
valued at north of 1.5 billion as well
as his fund AO aix
ventures. Today, Richard is co-founder
and CEO of Recursive, perhaps uh the
biggest moonshot he's ever taken, uh
focused on recursively self-improving
super intelligence. Richard, congrats on
a $670 million fund raise from Google
Ventures. Graycraft, Nvidia, and AMD and
410 million in compute from AWS.
Personal disclosure, I'm very proud to
be a seed investor in Recursive. And of
course, Richard, uh, important to
mention your new book just got released,
The Eureka Machine: Why AI is the key to
unlocking a new era of scientific
discoveries. Welcome to the pod,
Richard.
>> So great to be back.
>> And let me just add, a truly truly
awesome guy. A lot of people who listen
to the pot are worried about the the
ethics and the the risks and everything,
but boy, if you want a a person to
conquer recursive self-improvement that
you can like and trust, Richard is the
man.
>> Yeah.
>> Thank you so much. So great to be back
here. I love your guys. Constructive
optimism
in the world right now.
>> I have I have a bold prediction for this
episode.
>> What's that?
>> This one episode will prove our thesis
for this whole podcast more than any
other episode we ever record.
>> Awesome.
Let's go.
>> Let's go.
>> And uh uh Alex, do you know Richard?
>> Yeah, Richard, you and I have chatted
quite a bit. I don't think we've
actually ever met in person, though.
>> Really?
>> We have not. And it's the first time on
a podcast together. It's going to be
awesome.
>> Amazing. Well, let's make history.
>> Yeah, for sure. So, uh Richard, let's
start with your book. Uh the central
claim of the Eureka machine is that AI
will deliver a century of scientific
breakthroughs in the next decade.
uh you know this maps directly onto what
Alex and I wrote in solve everything. So
we're fans of that prediction. Uh your
thesis in the book is that every stage
of scientific process gets connected and
transformed simultaneously. Hypothesis,
experiment, data theory, you call it the
full stack AI. Uh you also say that
scientific progress has slowed and
that's been caused not by underfunding
but by fragmentation. So let's start
with those two items. Could you take a
moment and you know talk to us about
full stack AI for science and why you
think progress has slowed?
>> Yeah. So progress has slowed uh largely
because we have so many different subd
disccipline and uh disciplines and even
sus of lem uh realized like wow that
like if there are only so many people
and we have more and more fragmentation
of more and more subd disciplines and
niches like you can not just do AI right
you're doing often like optimization uh
and gradient descent methods and second
order derivative methods uh and so on of
uh these neural networks that is which
is one category of AI and so on. And the
same is true in biology. You study
biology, you're going to be either a
cell biologist or a molecular biologist
uh or you're like in medicine and like
these like there's so much separation
that it's hard to weave it all together.
And that is the perfect time for AI to
come in and help us weave back together
all these separate pieces and also help
us understand how these large complex
systems actually work. like we can't
have one model where humans say here are
all the things I know about natural
language and now like we can put all
these rules together and then we have a
conversation. It required a large neural
network with a ton of data. And guess
what? We're going to get a lot of data
uh about biology. And so we can make
more and more disciplines and move them
transfer them from being traditionally
natural sciences where we just try to
understand biology and nature to being
programmable engineering sciences. And
that I think is one of the many
different exciting aspects of things to
come. And you know why why am I so
excited that that this is happening
right now and and what are the major
ingredients? It's essentially that we
now have world knowledge in the form of
LMS. We have more and more scientific
data that's getting digitized that we
can sit on top of. We have better and
better simulations of things and we have
robotic process automation that will
soon be possible. And on top of that
we're going to have an agent swarm and
that is how uh this the full scientific
stack uh can be automated. Alex.
>> Yeah, I can say I disagree. As Peter,
you and I wrote in solve everything,
math, science, and engineering are
cooked. I'm curious, Richard, what your
latest timelines are.
>> I mean, the I think every field is going
to get to higher and higher levels of
abstraction. Computer science has been
very good at that, right? No one is
programming in zeros and ones anymore.
No one like very few people have to
still know C++ and complex pointers and
and memory uh architectures and so on.
we can get a larger and larger and
computer science has basically
abstracted enough so that it met the
rest of humanity with English, right?
And natural language that now can be
used to do computer science. And so I
think that um gives me great hope uh
that we can get other fields into
similar uh stages of abstraction and
then all meet and natural language to do
science. But to pin you down, as I
recall from my understanding of your
book, 3 to five years for the physical
sciences,
>> you know, like there's no like single
sort of this is the threshold and now we
solved all of physical sciences, right?
But like multiple different diseases
will get cured in the next 12 months.
They're going to be the simpler diseases
maybe where there's one gene that needs
to be fixed for that disease to be
cured. Um but there are a lot of single
gene diseases uh that that are out there
in aggregate, right? like and so those
diseases will get cured and then we're
going to cure more and more complex
diseases. We're going to develop better
and better battery material. So I
wouldn't call it like one threshold in
like in 3 years sort of everything is
solved but like we're going to solve
more and more problems and it'll just be
a question of how much money do you want
to put into compute to then solve which
kinds of problems?
>> You're you're talking to the guy Richard
remember who argues that the singularity
itself is something of an optical
illusion that there is no step function.
It's just a time interval. So I'll I'll
try once more timelines. When when even
if it's not a step function, when is the
inflection point when is the um 50%
point crossed in your mind for all of
the physical sciences getting solved?
All human disease getting solved? Where
are those timelines?
>> Alex, if I could just add a a layer on
top of that. So we've talked on this pot
a lot that math is cooked, right? We're
seeing millennium prizes all falling.
Yep. And the n the next natural uh if
you would uh uh barbecue is likely to be
physics
>> incineration.
>> Incineration. Yes.
>> And computer science arguably I mean
presumably this is part of the premise
Richard of recursive as well. Computer
science already cooked math thoroughly
cooked.
>> You know in a weird way I would I I
would use different metaphors. I think
they're flourishing not getting cooked.
I think the weird thing is, you know,
some some mathematicians recently said,
"Oh, this is this may be bad for the
field because like we need to train
people." Yes, we need to train people,
but imagine a biologist or or medical
researcher saying, "Oh, you know, it's
really a bummer for the field that we
cured all these diseases for people."
Like that would be insane, right? Of
course, you want to just move as quickly
as you can towards solving these
problems. I think maybe the problem with
math is that there's many sub fields in
of math that haven't really had there
are just almost purely beautiful
intellectual exercises without real life
impact anymore. But as you get close to
real life impact, you should be excited
about it and you think and realize your
field is flourishing, not being cooked.
Uh, and so to timelines, I think the the
further the more complex a disease is,
the more you have to do long-term
studies with humans before you're
allowed to put a certain drug into
humans, the more delays you will have.
But like we see now companies to make
this very concrete, biotech companies
used to have like one new drug in
development and it took them 10 years.
They had to go public before they knew
the comp the drug was really working.
And then after 10 years maybe late stage
three trials were just not working and
then the company is dead. Right now you
have in the new age of companies they
have 5 to 10 different compounds in uh
stage three trials after 2 or 3 years
and and so like we see a lot of
acceleration in that level but again
diseases to really be able to get them
into humans at scale in the United
States with FDA approvals there are just
some natural delays that will be more
like half a decade to a decade uh but uh
lots of other things in chemistry and
physics and so on where we can iterate
without having to look at long-term
human trials will be even faster.
>> And I the the the point is well taken. I
I like your Orwellian turn of phrase.
Maybe instead of saying AI is cooking
math, I should be using flourishing as a
transitive verb and just say AI is
flourishing math.
>> Actually, I was with Certas Caraman who
runs lids at MIT uh the night before
last. He he started a drone company now,
an AI drone company. But lids is where
radar was invented originally during
World War II. It's a great lab, very
entrepreneurial. But he said all his
mathematician friends at MIT uh are
aware that they're cooked and they're
they're all
>> No, no, Dave. Dave, we're going with the
Orwellian language now. They're they're
not cooked, they're being flourished.
>> He That's funny because he literally
said cooked, but I'll go back to him and
tell your friends they're flourishing.
>> Tell
not to worry. If your goal was to prove
as many theorems as possible in your
lifetime, like now is the time to just
grab like grab as many as you can and
and work with AI to solve them. And then
I think the field will change the way
computer science has changed in many
ways. Uh and it'll be much more about
what's the most creative thing when you
really understand all the things that
are out there in math. What kind of new
formalisms can you create? New
constructs can you create that then
would be interesting to be solved uh by
an AI in collaboration with humans.
>> Well, Cash was saying the math guys are
in great shape because they're so cooked
that they're all moving over to AI
orchestration and they're going to be
way ahead of the curve. He he's actually
most worried about the biology
professors who are in complete denial.
You using virtually no AI in their
day-to-day activities. And this is one
area where Richard, you have a such a
deep background in all facets of AI,
including biology. And I I feel like
we're living exactly parallel lives
except you're 15 years younger than me.
So I'm like insanely jealous of of your
life trajectory. But be a serial
entrepreneur, then start a hugely
successful venture fund, then found a
foundation model company. And and you
know, we're seeing the world through the
exact same lens. But you and Peter have
much more biology background. I I have
basically none. uh but the biologists
are the ones really really lagging and I
I think you've got a bunch of
investments actually that are that have
done really well in the area right
>> and I would love to talk about some of
those like peril bio proximal labs Ignod
labs like truly exciting companies I
think another field that is even more
lacking than biology is economics
economics literally has these models of
like
>> a linear model of economics right a
one-step economy that's provably
correctly taxed and and subsidized and
things like that it's just like absurd
how slow that field is to adopt AI for
making better policy decisions
ideology
>> because you opened the door. Eric
Bolson, our very good friend, uh I did
not realize till yesterday that HI lab
high at Stanford invented the word
foundation model
>> and he sent me the whole you didn't you
knew that already? Wow.
>> Yeah, of course. Like lots of Stanford
friends and Percy Lang and others uh
worked on foundational models. I love
Eric Goffson. actually one of the most
interesting economists I think uh doing
really interesting research right now.
He also started work helix which we're a
proud investor in uh that brings uh like
understanding of how companies actually
adopt AI uh and which tasks are getting
you know helped by in real rollouts for
companies. Uh yeah he's a co-founder of
that too.
>> Yeah building is just such a great place
cuz you talk about econ people being way
off the curve but he is so ahead of the
curve. You walk into the building and
you can just feel it. He's also poaching
a ton of talent from MIT to come out to
to join his lab,
>> following his path. Richard, talk about
full stack AI as you see it in the
scientific method. Um, you know, I'm an
investor in a company called Laya out of
MIT and Harvard. You know, Lyla science
as well. Uh, I think I've introduced you
to to Jeff von Maltson there. and you
know they're building a scientific super
intelligence that is then running a
million square foot of robotic space to
sort of like a thousandx the rate of
discovery. Um your thoughts on that?
>> I absolutely love it. I think that is
you know in the Eureka machine I sort of
lay out these four pillars and they're
actually one of the few um uh that that
are really going after this similar to
periodic labs who are doing it more on
the physics and chemistry side of
things. Uh, and there are several other
companies now that I can hopefully soon
talk about that are trying to create
more data for the bitter lesson to be
applicable in biology. And I love uh
what you know the big guys Eli Liy and
others do uh and and Laya too. I think
you know the ultimately uh you can boil
down the scientific method to the
ideation implementation and validation
of ideas and the faster we can close
that loop and then put an open-ended
process on top of it that's what
open-endedness uh what inspired us a lot
at recursive and we have many of the
world's greatest uh like researchers in
that subdomain of AI that is still not
quite as popular as it could and should
be um like the more you can have a swarm
uh innovate in open-ended ways and
evolve uh and combine interestingly
different ideas the better. But then of
course in biology you have to have uh
like actual uh like physical biological
wetwware experiments. And so it's really
great to see um uh Laya doing that. Um
we're seeing this also maybe I can talk
about this one company that I really
love called Peril Bio. They build tiny
organoids on a petri dish,
>> right? And get this, if you love
animals, you too can love AI. Why?
Because they got FDA approval to skip
animal trials. Turns out we cured most
diseases in mice. It's not that helpful.
They're very different to people. Uh but
these guys uh use pur potent stem cells
create tiny little organoids of lymph
nodes. Lymph nodes big part of your
immune system. Imunotherapy some of the
most exciting therapies to allow your
own immune system to attack a cancer and
so on instead of getting crazy
chemotherapy and so on. And so they got
FDA approval because they showed that
when you run experiments in parallel,
hence parallel bio in these tiny petri
dishes, how those organoids react to
different drugs and toxicity testing and
so on is actually more predictive of how
those drugs will interact in real human
bodies. And that is just one of many
beautiful examples of where it will
help. And you can take my stem cell, you
can create take my skin, create in a uh
IPSC uh cell, grow my own organs and see
how a particular drug would work for me
versus a generic individual. Uh Salem,
you want to jump in?
>> Uh yeah, a couple of things. One is, you
know, science has always been a
coordination problem, right? You're kind
of trying to bring and it's always been
very structured into departments and and
journals and all that stuff. And I love
what you're doing, bringing it together.
For me, if I had to summarize what you
seem to be doing is you're collapsing
the time between an experiment and a
result or hypothesis and a result. And
when you can collapse that, that's
domain collapse of the scientific
method. And now like anything is
possible from there. This is amazing.
>> Yeah. I I am going to push again on what
what Alex said, physics. When do you you
know you know Einstein's theory
relativity comes out. There's not that
much progress uh you know since then. a
lot of theories. Do you see physics as
the next domain that's going to flourish
on the back of math?
>> I think the biggest domain is actually
going to be biology. Physics has been
interestingly stuck in many ways like
they there's a really powerful ideas
like E= MC². So you can get a ton of
energy out of potentially little mass
and then we got nuclear energy out of
that. uh and so that then moved into and
graduated in some ways into an
engineering discipline uh which is where
you have the real real life impact. Um I
think you know obviously like fusion
will be great to finally get figured out
and there's a lot of really cool like
companies and and big labs and you know
tokomax already to balance uh like
plasma inside tokomax like is a very
hard control problem that where AI is
being used. Um I hope we can eventually
make better theories for uh you know
quantum gravity and all kinds of other
complex issues and and have get a better
world sort of formula. Um I
unfortunately the data set collections
these days require often like large
hydron colliders and just like billions
of dollars and it's like quite expensive
actually. So in a weird way, biology is
a better fit for AI because what
calculus did for physics like
understanding really well micro uh
individualized separated phenomena,
neural nets are great in combining all
these little things like we know what
the neuron does. We know what one uh
bacteria does in our microbiome, but
then as they all come together and form
these really complex interactions, we
don't really know anymore how that
works. And so that's where I I think
will help us more. Yeah, Alex,
>> let's talk about biology a bit. So, do
you think the critical path to solving
biology goes through digital twins of
cells or do you have some wildly
different theory of the case? Three
years ago when I started Eureka Machine
book, I had this chapter on the virtual
cell and I was really proud of like
trying to lay it all out and I had to
rewrite that whole thing because in the
meantime uh you know Mark Zuckerberg
Foundation started virtual cell
everyone not just CI everyone has a
virtual cell model Dave Even if Dave
doesn't even if Dave doesn't think Dave
has a virtual cell model I'm sure he'll
spin one up soon. So I think that most
So there's this famous uh uh paper by
Rich Sutton um on the bitter lesson in
AI and the
>> never heard of it. Tell me all about the
bitter lesson. This is a new concept for
me. What what is this you speak of?
>> I don't know. You're probably joking but
pro maybe some some readers haven't
heard of it. So the bitter lesson is
basically that human experts had all
these really clever ideas and beautiful
theories but really what you needed to
do was the simp like to make real
progress is the simplest method that you
can come up with a large neural network
that you can train end to end as a
general function approximator. The
simplest model you can come up with and
then it's just a ton of data and compute
to like actually train that model and
that usually outperforms at scale all
the clever little hacks that human
experts had come up with uh before. And
so the bitter lesson has worked for NLP
10, 20 years ago. You would have asked
an NLP expert. Can you have one model to
have any conversation with you prompted
any kind of question prompt engineering
I like invented and was nicely cited by
the early GBT papers. But like the same
thing, the same state uh is biology is
currently in. There's so many
complexities and the experts know so
much. They feel like there's no way you
can instill all of that knowledge into
one model. But if you have enough data,
you can. And now you have companies like
Tahoe therapeutics and so on that are
creating these massive perturbation
studies and yes all models are wrong but
more and more of them will be useful as
we collect more and more data about
biology and that is I think one of the
biggest driving factors uh for the
impact of AI.
>> But so ju just to answer the question do
you think virtual cell models are the
critical path to solving all disease or
solving biology or is it something else?
>> I I think they're definitely going to
play a crucial part. It's the third
pillar of the Eureka machine. We do need
to have anything you can simulate,
anything you can verify, AI will then be
able to solve things in that domain. And
so yes, uh I do think uh virtual models
uh and simulations uh are extremely
important.
>> I'm going to jump into three fun
breaking stories this week. Two on
science and one on AI. Uh and Richard,
they you know relate back to your work
and your book. Uh our first story was
published in MIT Tech Review today. Uh
it tells the story of researchers at
Israel's Weissman Institute who built a
system called brain it. The system
reconstructs the image a person is
looking at while inside a functional MRI
machine. I I'm just post put up the
slide here. So take a look at this
image. You know it's pretty
extraordinary. On one side is the image
that a person is looking at inside the
fMRI machine. On the other is the AI
reconstruction. You know, so earlier
brain image decoders could tell you were
looking at a dog or a clock tower, but
it lost the color, the composition, and
the detail. So brain it learns structure
and meaning separately and then puts the
picture back together. And here's the
clever part. They also can run the model
in reverse. An encoder that predicts how
a brain will respond to an image. So
they can feed it images no human has
ever seen into the scanner uh generate
predicted brain scans and then train on
those. The model effectively builds its
own data set. So Richard you know you
say in your book that AI is superhuman
in any domain you can simulate or verify
uh and nowhere else. So is a brain
simulatable do is the brain a
simulatable domain or is this something
different? It's not yet uh but this is
still an incredible result. I still
remember the first such result came out
when I was still a PhD student. I went
over to the bioinformatics department at
Stanford and they you know it's like
very grainy little images we could like
extract uh from this and to see this
fidelity now and this realism is just
incredible. I think one of the problems,
I don't know if this study, I haven't
seen it today yet, have been in the
work, but like um one of the problems is
often that you have to train for each
brain because they're all slightly
different. Uh and so you won't be able
to just take someone who've never put
into an fMRI scanner to see and update
the model for that particular person,
which would be otherwise amazing for
people who are like in a coma and you
want to see are they still thinking
stuff, you know, like that would be
incredible.
>> Alex, tell us more about this about this
story today. Yeah. So this actually this
is a result from March. Uh so this the
broader field of doing decoding of brain
states from functional imaging or EEG or
electrodes. This has a long long history
at this point. I remember 20 plus years
ago at this point the the Galant lab at
UC Berkeley was doing this to decode the
the visual cortex of cats. Actually like
20 plus years ago we were starting to
see images of how a cat perceives the
world. And I remember like the first
grainy images that were coming out were
like a cat seeing a branch. And then
moving fast forwarding to non-invasive
fMRI. There are so many groups at this
point. Meta in particular has been
sponsoring quite a bit of work in this
area from Jean Marie King, many other
groups doing language decoding, vision
decoding.
More recently, even fast forwarding to
just the past 24 hours, Neurolink just
announced their first scaling law
studies on pre-training foundation
models, Frontier models off of Neurolink
electronic data, and this is on an
individual patient basis, but they're
capturing copious amounts of of data at
high temporal resolution, much higher
than fMRI can capture. fMRI like rule of
thumb fMRI can give you with today's
technology at best cubic millimeter
spatial resolution for voxels and at
best approximately 1 second temporal
resolution. So that somewhat limits how
well you can do in terms of decoding a
person's internal visual state. can
still make no mistake there are folks
who have are making a cottage industry
out of decoding dreams uh and decoding
visually what a person perceives or what
they hallucinate in their visual cortex
while they're sleeping or while they're
awake and I'm sure this is going to be a
vibrant vibrant space training frontier
models and foundation models off of
copious amounts of fMRI data but
ultimately where I think this has to go
there are spatial and temporal limits to
fMRI decoding It's going to require
higher temporal precision and higher
spatial precision to get where we really
want to go, which is full dive VR and
full bandwidth BCIs. And we will get
there, but the good news is you have to
start somewhere. The large language
models had to start with GPT1, just a
single artificial neuron that could
predict the polarity of Amazon reviews.
Similarly here, if we're going to get
full bandwidth BCIs, it's going to start
with studies like Brain It and John
Marie King and Jackalant. Amazing. Sem,
what what happens in the world where you
can know someone's thoughts?
>> Well, I think you you Let's be careful.
We're decoding the perception here, not
the actual thought. Right. That's like
quite a bit more comp. What's the other
than the brain regionalization
without a difference?
>> No. No. I think there there is a
difference.
>> No, when when you imagine, right? When
you imagine something in your mind, it
lights up the same neurons as when
you're seeing them.
>> That that's fine. That that's fine. Just
I just want to make sure we don't mix
the two because you can have thoughts
without necessarily the perceptions
around it. But you can definitely have
one without the other and the other
without the other. So uh but I think for
me the more interesting thing here is
you know we've spent billions of hours
typing things into little rectangles and
if we can change that interface to do a
more natural interface which is
interface directly with the brain. We
used to talk about this in our
singularity university lectures on
neuroscience is you know we still have
very little idea how the brain works but
you don't need to have know how it works
as long as you can interface effectively
with it and this I think gives us the
opening to give us really deep
interfaces and then that'll help us
figure out how the the brain works. I
>> I'll take the
>> you bring up a really Oh go ahead
Richard. Sorry.
>> Sorry. You bring up a really good point
which is I I read this result a while
back that there are two types of people.
Some people who think actually think in
sentences and other people when they
think they just have a fuzzy thought
cloud and only once they're asked to
verbalize their thought or they try to
write it down they actually like make a
real sentence out of their fuzzy thought
clouds. And I'm definitely a thought
cloud thinker. My wife is very much a
like sentence like in her head. She
actually thinks in actual sentences and
like there's no there's no like one is
smarter than the other anything. there's
like they're like equivalent. But like I
do think sometimes like writing is
thinking and like for me it is very
helpful if I have to really verbalize
something versus I just have the
thought. I'm just trying to think like
what does the world look like if the eye
could really just like extract my
thoughts and now I need to like
structure my thought clouds into
sentences more and more precise.
>> Richard, what would neural net training
look like if you took all text out of
it? No language at all. just train on
pure images and higher level thought
constructs, you you'd get a very
different neural net out the other side
and might actually think a lot more like
you do and less like your wife does. Cuz
>> I'm not sure.
>> Maybe maybe we should be taking the
position that anyone who doesn't have an
inner monologue is just a pea zombie
>> there. I got to throw one more thing in.
I remember we had one of the top
linguists in the world come in and speak
and we were like, you know, this must be
a bad time to be a linguist. nobody's
using spelling or grammar or anything
else like that. And he goes, "No, on the
contrary, this is one of the most
interesting times to be a linguist
ever." And we're like, "Wow, how come?"
And he said, "Cuz when you look at
emojis, it's the first time in the
history of human language that you can
symbolically send emotion because you
can digitally send emotions." And we're
like, "Wow, that's an interesting." So,
he was super excited by opening up that
whole aperture. I thought that was an
interesting
>> You're saying you're saying you're
saying that emojis are the reason why
linguistics and not the fact that
linguistics itself has been flourished
by
>> I'm not connect I'm not connecting to
you did that though it's not me
>> Dave
>> oh no the the result I really am looking
forward to is uh how does the brain
>> train itself without gradient descent
everything going on in AI right now
everything going on for the last 20
years in AI is driven by gradient
descent algor algorithms and the
biologists can't find anything even
vaguely like that in actual biology. And
so that that's you know I think with
with really detailed imaging we might
finally crack the code on what is the
fundamental learning algorithm that
changes the synaptic weights. It's not
it's not what we use for artificial
neural nets. It's it's something
different and if we discover that we
might find that neural net training can
be 10 100 a thousand a million times
more efficient. And so hopefully that'll
come out within a year. Could you define
gradient descent for our listeners?
>> It's funny, Ilia Sutskiver uh when when
he's on interviews, he's like there is
only one algorithm. The algorithm is
gradient descent. Everything else is
just irrelevant compared to So what
happens right now is you build these 96
or 120 layer deep neural nets and all it
is is a whole bunch of random
connections that do absolutely nothing
useful and then you give it trillions of
15 trillion training examples. You're
like, "When you see this, say that or
when you see this paragraph, this is the
next token." And if you're guessing
wrong, you get punished through gradient
descent. So the error or the how far off
you are is your punishment and it passes
back through all the layers and it
calculates an error and it blames each
neuron or each connection for how how
responsible were you for this terrible
answer. And if you're way wrong, you get
moved and you move in the direction that
helps you get the answer right. So it's
this incredibly laborious search process
and that movement of each synaptic
connection is a gradient and you just
you just hill climb to the best possible
state and then it magically after about
hund00 million of comput in Richard's
case I guess 400 million uh it magically
starts thinking through this one
algorithm gradient descent.
>> Yeah I think it's really back back prop
that we're talking about syndictoically
rather than gradient descent would be
the the obvious comment. So maybe yeah
back prop is I guess the efficient
computation of those gradients. Uh maybe
I'll I'll add to um add to this
explanation from Dave but like gradient
is essentially an optimization algorithm
that we use to train all kinds of
machine learning models by minimizing
the errors. And I think the best analogy
is to assume you're a blind hiker.
You're the top of the mountain and
you're trying to find the lowest the
lowest point and you can't really see
that far. You're blind but you can feel
the slope at each step. And so how much
like how big of a step should you take
down when you feel like the slope is
going roughly in the right direction.
And then the problem is that the kinds
of landscapes these AIs are trying to
optimize are highly non-convex which
means there's not just one lowest point
uh but there are many different low
points. And if you depending on where
you start you might go into a different
valley depending on which mountain you
start you go into this valley versus
this this different valley. And there
are actually a lot of really interesting
analogies. My friend Jihan uh like
thinks about this from the psychological
perspective. For instance, when you have
PTSD and you train, you overfit to one
algorithm. how your brain is kind of
stuck in one valley of how to think
about something. And it takes sometimes
people like doing psychedelics and stuff
uh that have shown to to help help with
like depression and PTSD and other uh
mental diseases like um they they it
helps to increase the learning rate to
jump over another mountain and and go
into a different valley of attraction
where you then have new kinds of ways of
thinking. And so this blind hiker
analogy I think is a really intuitive
way to think about it. And then of
course the problem is it's not just in
3D, it's in a trilliond like a trillion
parameters that you're trying to
traverse in that landscape. But the
ideas of like try to identify the
direction and take steps towards it
still.
>> And you know what else is really
incredible? I could grip on this for
hours, but if you look at a big model
like Kimmy K3, it's 93 layers and it's
trained trained trained. If you take a
single layer and you randomize it and
then you train it and say find yourself
again, it can't find itself again. It
never gets back to where it was. Which
comes back to in these fMRIs when you're
looking at a human brain and you're
saying, "Okay, here's Alex's brain. Can
I compare that to Salem's?" And you're
like, "Wow, there's nothing in common
going on here yet." you know, well,
okay, maybe that's a bad example, but
but
the way your brain wires as you learn is
completely unique to you. Yet, yet it
can come out with like, okay, we're
equally good soccer players, but the way
the signals are propagating through our
networks is completely different and
unique to each of us, which is really
really strange, you know, that that it
can't it can't find its own way back to
its its state. I think we're going to
learn a lot actually with the fMRI data
coming in on how and why that works. And
there there have to be commonalities
that we just can't find. You know,
rotations, you know, make everything
look different, but they're really not
that different. If you if you put them
through a transform, like a 4A transform
view will suddenly say, "Oh my god, this
is why they line up."
>> Yeah. I was I was just with my
fraternity brother uh of ours, Dave,
who's the head of neurobiology at at USC
the other day. um and is you know this
is the most exciting time ever for brain
science
>> right I mean we're you know the brain
has been a black box for for since
humanity began and our ability to
understand
uh the brain and deal with with uh you
know mental disease I think is going to
be extraordinary. Yeah. Well, so you can
simulate. This is why liquid AI was
founded actually because we completely
reverse engineered the the C elegance
worm brain down to exactly every single
thing going on and then they were able
to simulate it and then after they
simulated it they realized wait this is
a very efficient neural net and then
they productized it. I mean that's so
the both ang so go ahead Richard
>> there's a really cool thing since you
mentioned se against worms there's not
many people that bring that up a friend
of mine who's a professor of
neuroscience at Harvard Sam Gershman uh
he one of the most brilliant people I've
ever met like he actually did a a study
with with worms where he cut them in
half and one segance worms they do have
a brain right and then they have a lot
of other like neurons in the rest now
you can train them to react to a certain
stimuli um and then you split them in
half the the second half without the
brain regrows a new brain. And here, get
this, this is crazy. That new brain has
the same memories.
>> Wow.
>> And reacts to different stimuli. And so
he's like, maybe there's a different way
where we learn. And I do think there are
things that right now we're very much
stuck in this like it's a neural net,
it's all electrical signals and so on.
But clearly like brain chemistry can
change massively with just like you can
get hangry, you can be in pain, you can
have like a certain like stimulant and
all of a sudden your brain is very
different. And I think there are and
I've seen this now with uh like uh
having babies and and like talking to uh
moms like there's certain algorithms
where you all of a sudden you nest
because you had a baby and now you want
to like and how you nest is different
but people nest you know in one form or
another and so there are these latent
algorithms that we have that are in our
DNA that just trigger after like 20
something years right when just the
right things then happen with your body
and your biology. So, I think there's
still so much that we don't we haven't
>> so much complexity. I'm going to move us
to our next story from three days ago.
So, on Tuesday, uh the president signed
an executive order directing the EPA,
the Department of the Interior and
Agriculture working with HHS to cut
invasive mosquito populations in
Washington DC by at least 90% and the
tick population by at least 50% by 2028.
Uh, the targets include mosquito species
that spread deni, zika, and yellow
fever. And here's what caught my eye.
You know, the order explicitly
prioritizes sterile insect techniques,
safe genetic modifications, and
beneficial bacteria over conventional
pesticides, right? I love that. You
know, this is the exact kind of uh gan
drive work that Colossal, the
deextinction company, is doing. You
know, I think most people don't realize
it's like, you know, when I was raising
my kids, I would ask them a question,
who which which is the species that
kills the most humans on the planet, you
know, and some people jump onto sharks?
Some people jump onto, you know,
whatever it might be. But, uh, on this
part, I'm sure people know mosquitoes
are the deadliest life form on Earth,
>> right? Malaria alone, uh, kills half a
million people a year. So, uh, Alex, u,
this is biology as engineering arriving
as federal policy. Uh, your thoughts on
this story? For decades, we've been
scared of our shadow. So, I have a
classmate Kevin Esfelt at MIT who was
the pioneer of the GAN drive, one of the
pioneers, and he's had a devil of a time
getting states, municipalities to
approve gan drive studies against
mosquitoes. And for those not tracking,
the the premise of this technique is
basically inserting a gene via crisper
that wants to replicate itself to
basically sterilize mosquitoes through
propagating virally through the mosquito
population. We have the technology to do
this. What it has lacked, at least in
this country, is a federal mandate to
actually go and implement large-scale
genetic engineering of non-human animal
populations. And now for the first time
it seems we're seeing via executive fiat
just that mandate. And it is so exciting
for two reasons. One because one is
Peter you mentioned malaria and other
non-human animalborn diseases cause an
an enormous amount of suffering human
suffering and also non-human animal
suffering. But secondly because there's
a way to do this that doesn't actually
involve killing the animals themselves.
Historically,
historically, you know, if you look back
50 years, you'd see chemical spraying if
you wanted to do something about say
insect born illness
uh responses. We don't need to do that
anymore. We can actually keep the
insects that are the inadvertent
carriers of bacterial or viral disease.
We can actually preserve their lives
while also preventing the disease
transmission. And I think that's good
from their perspective as well. That was
the part that got me most excited was we
spray things, we're basically poisoning
biology now we actually
>> ecosystem, right?
>> And leave the poison ecosystem.
>> Yeah. Yeah.
>> Uh Richard, your thoughts on this story?
>> I I concur with everyone like it's it's
it's wonderful. Uh and it's so
interesting like people I I hope we can
amplify these these kinds of stories
more, you know, like the future needs
better marketing. We need more Peters in
the world. Um and and this is one of
those many stories, you know, curing
various diseases, peril bio, like saving
animal lives and and prevent them from
just being bred uh to be tested upon and
dissected like uh those are all like
stories we need to amplify more in the
public eye. Yeah, Dave, I can't wait for
this to come from DC to Vermont and
Massachusetts and all of these
>> I was going to say for the listeners
that are interested in your real estate
fund, which you know the the theme there
is, hey, easy access via drone to
hilltops, islands, but also if you live
on the edge of a marsh, your house
probably sells for about half the price
of a place that's not on the edge of a
marsh, that'll go away. there there's so
many solutions coming to biting insects,
this being one of them. Uh that that
also is is, you know, if it's beautiful,
beautiful land that otherwise is very
difficult to live on, it's going to go
through the roof in value.
>> I do think it's really important to try
to like, you know, keep the bees uh like
alive, all right, and not have spray
bunch of pesticides, make sure birds
still have enough like insects to eat
and things like that. Yeah,
>> I was going to say for maybe up to 80
years, humanity has been scared of its
own shadow. humanity in general, America
or the West in particular, nuclear
energy. Another example I've pointed out
on the pod where we arguably lost 50
plus years of progress because we were
too scared of either the bomb or fision
reactors or some an entire generation
watched the movie China Syndrome and
then got scared of nuclear power
unnecessarily. Same idea with this or or
with geoengineering. Another example,
the the world is still scared. Some
fraction of the world is scared of
engineering the weather. We don't need
to be scared of engineering our physical
world or our biological world. And now
hopefully one can see green shoots of
humanity getting past that stage of
worrying about its own shadow.
>> This is interesting that Sorry. Yeah,
it's really it's interesting indeed that
like sometimes alarmists feel like
they're doing the right thing by just
like oh how bad could it be? I'm warning
people of something bad. But like it can
indeed push all of humanity away from
something really good like energy
abundance uh with nuclear. Um I think
overpopulation is when these other big
myths where people are like well if we
have too many people there's going to be
scarcity of all these different
resources and everything is going to get
more expensive and people are more
poverty and so on and the exact opposite
happened. There's actually one website
that I think you all would love which
called humanprogress.org or.com like
that that shows that a lot of these
things are actually getting cheaper and
cheaper despite there being more people.
>> Yeah.
>> Well, hey Richard, you're you're a hero
in Germany like like can't walk down the
street kind of hero in Germany. What do
you think about the fact that Germany
has no power for exactly this reason?
>> It is really unfortunate if there are a
lot of people in Germany that want to in
a weird way sort of offramp from
progress. Um and they think that
everything that consumes power is bad
for the environment. there's like a
weird sort of degrowth uh offshoot from
generally like well-intentioned pro-
like environmental uh vibes that uh just
worry me um worry me quite a bit. Yeah,
>> we're going to talk about dumerism in a
little bit uh but not yet. And you know,
one of the things I realized a long time
ago is we humans are really incredible
at seeing a problem out in the future,
right? We see acid rain, we see
overpopulation, we see, you know, energy
shortage, whatever it might be. And then
because of our amigdula, because the way
we think, we accelerate that future
problem to today. And we freak out and
we forget the fact that there is a
decade worth of progress we're going to
make by the time we reach that problem.
And that's what entrepreneurs do. They
solve problem after problem after
problem. And I I guess I just want our
listeners to hear that because if you're
worried about some future problem,
please understand there's a incredibly
efficient market uh of entrepreneurship
and capitalism that will solve the
world's biggest problems, the world's
biggest business opportunities, right?
And it's a beautiful uh forward uh you
know uh uh forward propagation solution
set that we have. And maybe we'll get
there later, but I I see the same thing
happen in AI dumerism where they create
more and more complex scenarios where
attackers get these like near magical
abilities to attack, but somehow the
defenders in those stories never get
near magical abilities to defend. And
it's this weird thing of like, man, if I
can create a super virus that is like
perfectly undetectable and spreads all
throughout the world and no one notices
it and like and then it has this Wi-Fi
switch and you just turn it on and off
and kill people like I I will create a
super magical vaccine that just
inoculates you against all of these
things. Like if you can actually assume
make that assumption then like it's a
weird Yeah. weird thing.
>> This episode is sponsored by Google for
startups. Think about this for a second.
You now have access to the same
generative AI models that cost hundreds
of millions of dollars to train.
Google's startup technical guide for
generative media gives you complete
blueprint for deploying Google DeepMinds
models in production. Images, video,
audio, all of it. Real architecture,
real results. Find the link in the show
notes below.
I'm going to move us to a story that's
been sort of breaking the internet over
the last 24 hours. Um, and it it puts
your regulate the application argument
to the test, Richard. So, a company
called Tavis unveiled Griffin, uh, which
it calls the first model ever to pass
the video touring test. So, here's the
numbers. 48% of people who talk to an AI
avatar on a live face-to-face video
thought they were talking to a real
human. Previous systems were at 3%. So,
let me show the video here. And uh it's
super cool and let's talk about it next.
>> Now, how about just a thumbs up?
>> Sure. One thumbs up coming right up.
>> Hell yeah. That was awesome. I would say
you're my favorite coworker. It's been
It's been really great toh work on this
with you.
>> You're making me blush. A Who's that
with the ugly sweater?
>> Simon says, "Touch your hair."
>> Is this what you're looking for?
>> Yeah. Okay, nice. Simon says point. All
right, I'm doing it.
Now, touch your chin.
>> I'm not going to fall for that. You
didn't say the magic word. Uh,
>> you got me. Okay.
>> The loose connector back onto the
motherboard.
>> Okay, let me go let me go grab that. But
beforehand,
yeah, I turned the soldering iron on. I
think it's going to take about 12
seconds. So, maybe just let me know when
that's done.
>> It sounds good. I'll keep an eye on it
and let you know the second it hits that
12 second mark.
>> All right. So, uh, interesting. So,
Tavis calls it the first human
interaction model. It's fully duplex,
listening and talking at the same time
that you do, the way humans actually do.
It's number one on Nvidia's benchmark
for full duplex AI video. Tavis pitches
it as quote a tutor for every student
that notices when they're lost, an elder
care companion that listens. Uh Tavis
itself says Griffin requires safety work
before it can be released publicly
because it's the first model that can be
mistaken for a real person. Um Salem,
your thoughts on this one?
So, I'm less kind of um floored by the
um the imagery and the the mimicry of
it. Uh this was expected to happen. For
me, I'm more interested in can it
accomplish something useful enough that
I don't care whether it's human or not.
And I think that that is more
interesting uh which might come along
and have hap we have that happen at some
point. We've talked about the idea that
in the near future, like now, uh you're
going to have digital co-workers that
pop up on Zoom, that you call, that you
text, you Slack, and interact with you.
And I think it's pretty compelling as a
mechanism for a future, you know,
virtualized company. Uh Alex,
>> well, first, Peter, you should probably
ask me to touch my face.
>> Okay, touch your face. Simon says touch
your face.
>> Oh,
>> okay. Very good. Just checking but I I
guess Tavis is ahead of me. I I I think
on the one hand if you look at models
coming out of Chinese labs like
Alibaba's lab, Juan Streamer gave us a
preview of what was going to happen. The
Chinese labs remain overinvested
relative to the Western labs in
generative video models and interactive
generative video models. So one streamer
I think is a preview of what's possible.
My guess is I I I I I read the the
information that was put out around
Tavis. I I think in full generality, let
let's just talk about where this is
going to end up. It's it's very
difficult to predict the short term. I
think it's pretty easy to predict the
long term. In the long term, endto-end
generative pixels. We'll have these
magic mirrors that could be real time
fully interactive pixel-wise generated
or if if anthropic has its way,
vector-wise or procedurally generated.
But either way, fully generated
real-time interactive video models and
you'll be able to create a scene that
consists of people like it's possible
right now, but the latency is high. You
see with one streamer, which is already
out and already open source, or with
this Tavis Griffin type model, which is
not really out yet and definitely not
open source. You see a preview of the
future. What does this look like? Well,
there are a few different ways it can
go. Query how revenue generating per
token it is. I is it anywhere close to
the optimal frontier of code generation?
Doubt it. On the other hand, if it
becomes so absurdly inexpensive to be
able to to generate arbitrary, say,
humans participating in a Zoom meeting
or humans participating in a podcast. Do
we really care whether it's close to to
being near the optimal cost performance
frontier? Maybe not. There are a lot of
human service industry jobs that require
a face and require interactivity and a
voice and the ability to touch one's
face apparently on demand or on on
request that could be probably
completely automated away by a model
that otherwise would be limited to
textbased interaction but doesn't have a
face and a voice. So in the most
optimistic scenario, these sorts of
interactive video models open PN note
that the acronym for this which by the
way was there first with Alex Finn him
him is such an obvious reference to her
the the movie closed PN I I think this
this has this
>> you should use you should use m dashes
please
>> okay I'll delve into it so I I I think I
I I think this is going to be
transformative for the service sector
And hopefully TAVIS and the broader
American west of video frontier models
and interactive video frontier models
take a page from Tavis and start
competing with China.
>> Richard, one of the principles in your
book, one of the rules you have is that
AI becomes superhuman uh where you can
verify the answer. uh and you know is
like passing a human scientific
milestone like this uh is passing sort
of a human judgment and interaction uh
you know sufficiently as a scientific
milestone for verification.
>> Not quite. Uh it's sort of like it's
hard to scale when a human has to be in
the loop to say yes this is like a human
another person on the other side or not.
Uh you can't quite automate it
completely uh and verify it in in that
automated fashion. Um I do think you're
you're right. This is a good example
where I think we need to do be go beyond
KYC and do KY know your use case. Uh
right like you don't want this
technology to be in Zoom pretending to
be the CEO and like there's some famous
stories where this has already happened
where they got someone to wire like $20
million cuz they created a Zoom with
five other executives and they all like
he was fooled well enough. Um and and so
I think we need to um yeah be careful
and like Zoom probably and Google
Hangout need to start like finding
countermeasures to identify is this a
real person and and things like that uh
to prevent those kinds of hacks from
happening.
>> Yeah, scams are going to proliferate on
this. I I just want to do a call out
again. And I've said this before on the
pod and if you're if you've not heard
this before, if you still have your
grandparents with you or your parents
and you've not taken the time to record
their stories on video and audio and go
deep, spend, you know, hours recording
them, right? Your ability to create a
super highresolution lifelike avatar for
your your kids or your grandkids or your
great-grandkids, I think, is an
incredible thing. But you need the data.
So, if you're listening to this and
you're lucky enough to have your parents
or grandparents around, collect their
data because it's going to be a
beautiful opportunity for your uh for
your progyny and theirs.
>> A andor I I should add get them an Elor
membership and preserve their conneto if
there is a consideration like what why
stop with just the behavioral data
preserve the whole parent.
You know, my kids my kids are in a deep
freeze or at least they're placental
cells.
>> But I have a push back on that just I
have a push back on that just from this
conversation.
>> If from the earlier story we can read
people's brains, all you have to do is
picture an image of your grandmother and
then extract it from that.
>> It'll be low low fidelity. I mean I I do
think like to to first order this is how
ancestor simulation will work. You see
stories left and right just in the past
48 hours of people using opus 5.5 or or
other frontier models to reconstruct
bits of history that would were
otherwise unknown just based on
artifacts of the day. But at some point
I I do think sem you want to go beyond
just the memory of the person and you
want the actual person. And I I'll pound
the the drum again in addition to Peter
you know very generous of you to
preserve the placenta associated with
your children but not necessarily your
children. I'm sure the placenta placenta
will will thank you. Uh but
>> yeah, go ahead. Finish.
>> But but I I I I would say like yeah, if
if if this is a serious concern, you're
worried about your parents or your
grandparents and you want to go beyond
just having recordings of them or a AI
prompted generative interaction models
of your ancestors. Go get them Alore
memberships and get them cryopreserved.
>> Yeah, Richard, really uh really curious
to ask you a question. And you know uh
we we clearly passed the touring test
and you know Sem's reaction is my
reaction that the what we just saw is a
so what if you've been using models
every day all day long you you know you
just had to stitch together the
components and you have but I but I
think this will show mainstream world
that we've crossed the Turing test and
then you know the next milestone is the
demos test where using information from
1910 and prior rediscovery equals MC²
uh so you can't cheat which is a really
tough one to measure because cheating is
is you know but without cheating only
using prior information come up with the
equals mc^ squ so is there a Soer test
that's like a really fun measurable
milestone coming
>> I I came up with the like uh anti-
touring test uh which actually I think
the whole touring test has flipped where
now in order to know whether there's a
human on the other side or not you
actually ask it questions that are so
hard no human could ever answer it. Like
if you asked an AI to just write you a
complex web app uh and like 10 seconds
later it comes back with like 50,000
lines of code, you're like you kind of
know it was not a human, right? So I
think that test has actually completely
flipped.
>> You don't think Richard I mean like you
it could throttle itself. That one's
easy to defeat. But just like basket now
it's just about it's just about fakery.
you like the reason it was an
intelligence test for artificial
intelligence was that it was so hard to
be as smart as a human. Now you just
have to throttle yourself down to human
level in order to pass the test which
makes the test useless as an inspiring
test for intelligence. Yeah, I think
perversely probably the best way to uh
like the best capture for knowing
whether you're inter interacting, this
is not a recommendation, but best way to
know whether you're interacting with a
textbased chatbot is probably to ask it
a CBRN related question and see if it's
capable of responding. Probably not.
>> Yeah. Uh let me just hit real quick uh
again for our listeners. If you're
pregnant or someone in your family is
pregnant, you know, uh
save their placental cells. One of my
portfolio companies called LifeBank USA
does this. That's where I've saved my my
kids placenta. You know, the placenta is
the 3D printer that manufactures the
baby and it has the stem cells, natural
killer cells, T- cells, exoomes, and
it's like from those cells, if my kid
should ever need any kind of biological
enhancement or organs, you've got the
original boot disc to use an old term,
uh, for your kid's DNA. So that's uh
LifeBank USA. Just I just think it's
like a moral obligation parents should
have to to save those cells uh as a
backup. Um
>> as a backup for your children. Could you
use it to replace your children, Peter?
>> You could you could use it to clone your
children. For sure.
>> And now now they know why you're banking
them.
>> Yeah, exactly. An army an army of young
demand. Uh Richard, uh let's jump next
into the core of what you're building at
recursive. uh namely recursive
self-improvement and super intelligence.
So let me ask a few sort of uh key
questions to kick this off. So first
where are we at the moment with RSI?
Number two, how do you define ASI? It's
been a long-standing debate. And then
how far away are we from ASI? So can you
hit those three?
>> So yeah, um I think there's
>> So where where are we at the moment with
RSI? So
this this year something major shifted
and that is uh AI uh can now code uh
right and that uh is a major shift uh in
in the ability for it to change itself
you know like we now are able to
essentially lean into the fact that AI
is code and AI can't code right so you
have a loop that you can close there uh
and so in various weak form forms. We
already have RSI. Um, and the weak forms
that even Enthropic OpenAI talk about
when they often talk about is like look
how much our employees, our engineers,
our programmers use codecs or claude to
create some code. And I would argue that
that is a weak form of uh recursive
self-improvement because you still have
like deeply embedded humans in that
loop. And what we're working on at
Recursive is to have humans only be
involved in setting up the rewards and
the environment and the goals and then
allow the eye to have the entirety of
the process of ideiation,
implementation, and validation of ideas
and have full control over that and
allow for so-called open-ended
algorithms, uh, evolutionary search
algorithms that combine interestingly
different ideas, uh, to really flourish.
And I like it's been incredible. But
like we have like forms of that going
already. Now where the the the sort of
physical reality hits is that you still
need a lot of compute. If you ask that
RSI to come up with really great forms
of itself, you need to give it a lot of
compute uh to come up and be able to
train very sophisticated versions uh of
itself. But this is going to take off uh
next year. Like it's uh I'm
>> So we're not there yet.
uh we're not quite there yet, but we're
very close. Like, and again, in weak
forms, there's already one. And then
there are other ways that people slice
and dice it. My friend Jason Weston, who
who's still at Meta, um he kind of wrote
a paper around this where you can think
about different axes, learnable axes of
self-improvement, the parameters, the
training data, the objective function,
the neural architecture, and the overall
code and the harness and everything
else. And no one has really cracked the
nut of doing all of these five plus um
like truly uh coming up with the ideas
on which of these dimensions and axes to
optimize for. Uh and you can know that
that has hasn't happened yet because all
the big companies are still hiring
thousands of engineers to do it manually
to a large degree with more and more
implementation help from an AI.
>> Your definition of ASI because I want
Sem to hear this. I think artificial
super intelligence uh has to spike uh uh
at the very least uh across uh several
different capabilities. Uh but in in the
grandest uh definition of it, it should
supersede not just arbitrary humans like
a touring test but all of humanity to
solve arbitrarily hard tasks. And
eventually uh I would argue there are 10
different spaces of intelligence that I
define in in the Eureka machine book
too. But eventually it cannot just
purely robotically do exactly what it's
told. It should have some capability.
And I'm not saying a sort of a mor moral
pro prerogative, but like um I would
argue that something isn't super
intelligent if it cannot choose to some
degree what it works on, right? And has
have some metacognition about its
thought itself. But uh generally the
most easy way to measure it is just
capabilities across many different
spaces of intelligence like visual
perception, communication, language,
social interactions and so on that is uh
beyond that of humanity and that we we
are still far away from
>> Elon's definition is as smart as all
humans combined. Is that yours?
>> Uh I would argue it's it's smarter than
humanity combined than then it's truly
super intelligent. occasionally and go
for it.
>> Well, it's I this is where I go bananas
because you say it's as smart as a human
being. Well, what the hell does smart
mean? Uh because I can be emotionally
smart and I can be I can have physical
intelligence if I'm an athlete or
linguistic intelligence or musical
intelligence. So, smarter seems to be a
very vague term to me in terms of what
do we mean by all of this? Can I just
shift the conversation just a bit? Um, I
made a list of things and I'd love for
you to I'm going to throw out the list.
You tell me where recursive
self-improvement begins, right? Because
I'm This is where I'm kind of stuff. So,
we've got a continuum of okay, AI writes
some code that the next model uses.
Number two, AI proposes some experiments
for uh researchers. Uh, number three, AI
runs those experiments or then it
evaluates the results. uh then it
modifies its own training system and
then it launches its next iteration of
itself without meaningful human
intervention.
So in that spectrum if whatever if those
are roughly a spectrum where did
recursion begin and that's where I'm
struggling.
>> It's a great question. Yeah, I we often
talk about the ideation, implementation,
and validation of ideas. And true
recursive self-improvement in its
strongest sense has to have all three of
these done by an AI in
>> So you have an inner loop for each of
them. Okay.
>> Exactly. And an inner loop and then
there has to be an outer process that is
more open-ended where the eye can
innovate and recombine interestingly
different ideas similar to biological,
cultural, and technological evolution.
Hm.
>> And and Richard to hit my third
question. When do you believe we reach
ASI?
Give me a time. Give me a time frame. So
I think in the I think in the strongest
sense the absolute strongest sense where
indeed uh like Salim uh mentioned there
is uh there are 10 spaces that I define
my book of intelligence, perceptual
intelligence, communication intelligence
uh like uh interaction uh sociological
intelligence, creative intelligence, the
speed at which you can do things uh meta
cognition and and so on uh knowledge um
reasoning mathematical reasoning and so
on. So there 10 of these spaces uh and
to be better than all of humanity
combined I think will take us probably
several decades. Um I think it's also a
bit of a change
>> shocking.
>> Yeah. I mean Elon says 2029 2030 latest.
Uh
>> I think those he probably means like
weaker forms of ASI where it is you know
like you can say it's better at
programming than all of humanity and
we'll get there. It it's it will be
better at math uh than all of humanity
and will like that that will be in a few
years. It'll be better at any game where
you can see all the parts of the game
like go and chess and so on. Like there
there are many areas where it will spike
to be better than humanity. But humanity
can build a large hydron collider.
Humanity can create a gold atom. Maybe
just a few atoms and takes a ton of
energy. But like we can create novel
like atoms like right and and different
molecules and so on. there's it's going
to take a while before we even give uh
AI the access to the physical world such
that it can innovate in that way beyond
all of humanity right and really build
like Dyson spheres and so on that it
will take some time
>> Alex
we're we're drinking we're drinking
different water as uh as our our our
frenemies in the uh in in the alignment
community would say I recognize that I'm
confused and I recognize that I'm very
confused Right now, Richard, you you're
running a recursive self-improvement
company, but you think super
intelligence is 20 years away. What are
you thinking?
>> So, again, how do you reconcile
intelligence?
>> I think I think super intelligence will
spike and there will be areas where it
will be super intelligent and that is
like algorithmic development for
instance, uh programming, uh and again
AI is code, AI can code, and that will
be a super uh human capability and and
is in many ways already. Um, we just
have to be realistic that like there are
certain physical constraints, right,
about like physical control. Controlling
your own substrate, allowing your
computational substrate to be modified
will require like novel supply chains.
It will require novel like materials. It
will require ways for that AI to get
access and for us to give it access to
building new ASML. Like think about the
machine of ASML that actually creates
these like one two nanometer like chips
right that is just like it will take
more than 2 years to build such a
machine even if you had the perfect
blueprint for
>> it might take I mean it might take 3
years for Elon's free electron laser to
replace ASML which is propping up half
of Europe's economy but I don't think
it'll take more than three years
I
>> yeah like wildly wildly
>> all that itself Yes, of course. Like I I
I from my perspective, hooking a AI up
to the physical world, like giving it
model control protocol or hardware
control protocol, whatever anthropic
decides to brand it as these days,
that's the easy part. Giving it access
is easy. I like if it's super capable,
giving it access to armatururs. We
talked in a previous pod about what
happens when you just take Astra
straight out of the box and you drop it
into a car. It's able to drive a car. If
you give it the controls, it knows how
to use them increasingly. I don't think
manipulating the physical world is an
obstacle at all. Completely don't buy
the 20-year timeline. Putting that aside
and that apparently I'm drinking very
different singularity water that you
>> I agree with you, Alex, for what it's
worth.
>> Thank you, Peter. Um I I I do want to
ask though, so uh putting issues of
timelines aside, I I am curious as to
whether we can at least agree on what
the end of the rainbow looks like. So
say we we run this recursive
self-improvement story to its
conclusion. What does the end state of
what is the fixed point of recursive
self-improvement look like? What is the
perfect AI model architecturally look
like at the end of the day?
>> Yeah. Uh I think one uh it would be uh
hubris for us to know uh right now.
>> No no but it's just Richard it's just us
talking like no one else is listening.
It's okay. You can tell me it it's this
is a this is a safe model space
>> in this whole conversation actually
>> it's safe Richard you can tell me what
you think how this ends
>> uh so I guess there different ways to
answer that question of like how like
with the exact model architecture and
there's some things I can share it with
recursive uh that we're working on but
like I do think uh that state will be
incredible uh I think we will that AI
will be able to innovate and out
innovate on along any dimension that we
want it to innovate I think most
diseases will be uh curable with enough
funding. Uh and then again just to like
say like to pro prove my point like to
get a drug through FDA long-term trials
takes a few years. I would argue ASI
will have cured all diseases and can
cure all of them but just to know
whether that happened will take more
than 3 years. Even if we had all
compounds ready to go and be
manufactured like tomorrow like just
because of FDA things. So there's some
there's some like
>> but we have we have cell simulators that
are going to be able to demonstrate and
prove definitively that in this cell
your cell this drug works. I mean the
idea of human trials is going to get
incinerated. I think I mean
>> I know it's going to get it's going to
get flourished. We're we're using
Richard Everything's flourished at this
point. That'll be a new new t-shirt P
flourish. It's funny. I usually on all
podcasts I'm the one who is the optimist
and maybe here I'm like I'm I'm still an
optimist. I think this will all happen.
We're just disagreeing on timelines and
it makes me kind of feel like I'm I'm
the pessimist. But like I I I believe
virtual cells are are amazing. Cells are
incredibly complicated. If we want them
to be really really perfect, we cannot
currently measure all the proteins that
happen in one cell without destroying
that cell, you know, like and so these
perturbation studies for instance that
Tower Therapeutics are working on like
they're taking they're adding one
molecule to one cell. They're seeing how
does that molecule change that one cell
and then they get one data point. We
need to like collect a lot of those data
points across a lot of different cells
without destroying each each cell in the
process. So you know the one cell is
very complicated. Once you have one
cell, you have multisellular like you
know organoids and you have to like put
those all together. I one thing that I
would love to start as a company if if I
had extra time which I don't right now
is is to actually build a system of
organoids where you can really have not
just like one lymph node but you have a
whole lympnatic.
>> It's being done. It's being done. I can
introduce you there.
>> This is a very eloquent
>> if I may. This is a very eloquent
distraction from recursive
self-improvement. this this little
sideline that we went on about cells,
but Richard, I I really do want to try
to pin you down on where recursive
self-improvement goes. So, you've been
very public about not nano GPT, but nano
chat. We talk on the pod all the time
about the nano GPT speedrun world record
collapsing. Just in the past week or
two, there was been
>> Oh, you just wait for a few more days.
There will be another really fun update
there.
>> Amaz
speedrun.
>> Yes. Yes, that both of those
>> give us a few days.
>> Okay. So, so but let
>> just quickly you're next. Let Alex
finish up
>> to to pin this down though. So, so I'm
standing by for the major update on nano
GPT world record speedrun. But there's
been major progress there without
requiring any new data scaling at all.
These are purely largely my perception
is recursive self-improvement
algorithmic improvements that have been
able to collapse the amount of time that
it takes to train a GPT2 class model.
And there's been a mini scandal brewing
in the community over the past 2 weeks
over a collapse from whatever it was
like 60 or 70 seconds down to something
like 40 seconds by approaching the
problem differently and factoring out
world knowledge from the ultimate model
and hand ringing. Does that constitute
viable training of nano GPT if you
factor out all the world knowledge? So,
I'm I'm using this as an attempted
stealthy way to try to get you to at
least comment on whether you think that
the the the perfect model at the end of
the recursive self-improvement rainbow.
Does it at least factor out world
knowledge from a reasoning core or do
you think those always remain unified?
>> Can I ask interject one very quick thing
before Richard answers
>> please?
>> Which is that the definition of a
singularity is you can't see past the
event horizon once you have full RSI.
That's vertical. By definition, we can't
predict where it goes.
>> That's Ray's definition that I don't
subscribe to.
>> Disclaimer. I got that. Over to you.
Over to you, Richard.
>> Sorry. So your your question is do we
separate what exactly from
>> does does world knowledge a at the end
of recursive self-improvement once we
have our perfect model some would argue
that the perfect model should cleanly
factor out and segregate out world
knowledge which could live in a text
file or a database from the weights or
the parameters of the model which would
just be this perfect reasoning kernel
maybe could be a megabyte uh in size
doesn't need to be all these gigabytes
of memorization
What do you think?
>> Well, world knowledge meaning like
Taylor Swift videos and past Trump
tweets and all that like I I do think um
just like humans benefit from memorizing
things like in order to be able to
creatively think through concepts. So
does an AI. It an AI also has to have
that knowledge partially in its weights.
It's not going to be a perfect
separation for sure. You have to be able
to creatively play with concepts and
reasoning over these concepts required
you to to have some of that world
knowledge deep inside the model. And
then of course just like humans have a
search engine and we're building search
engines at.com for LMS like that there
will be a separate world knowledge thing
too but the the main model will have a
lot of that mixed in for sure.
>> Wow. Okay. Thank you. All right. Uh I'm
going to share an article that Salem you
brought to the table here. So while
we're talking about recursive
self-improvement, Washington wants to
ban it. Um so on Monday, Silicon
Valley's own congressman Ro Kana told
CNBC he's introducing what he calls the
most comprehensive legislation to date
on AI. It's called the Human Control
Over AI Act. At its core, the bill is a
ban on AI models that do what you want
them to do. Richard recursively
self-improve focusing on the need for
containment and the requirement for
shutting shutdown controls. The ban
would stay in place until federal uh
guard rails exist. Uh in his words,
there's actually a civilization
civilizational risk. Uh there's a safety
risk for loss of control and then
there's a misuse risk and we need to
take both seriously. The bill includes
criminal penalties for the work that
you're doing, Richard. uh and requires
independent auditors embedded in every
frontier lab reporting directly to the
government. Uh a recent poll by a group
called Common Dreams shows that 68% of
voters back a bill like this. So I'm
going to tie that story, Richard, to an
essay you just wrote called Why Doomers
Are Wrong. So uh if you would, what's
your reaction to this? And then I'd love
you to dive into the whole story of why
doomers are wrong.
>> Oh boy. Uh there's a lot.
>> It's an important one. We talk about
this a lot. You know, we're we're we're
injecting optimism into everyone's
neural net here.
>> I'll I'll try to try to distill it. Uh
but there is no realistic scenario where
AI wipes out all of humanity. Um you can
like number one
>> just 90%
what kind of reassurance is that Richard
>> P doom is zero uh so that that's number
one um
>> so like people like and and I've debated
many of these experts and after like 2
three hours they almost all agree when
if they're reasonable and they're not
just like well once we have RSI then 10
seconds later the AI will attack us from
the 15th dimension and we're all dead
and it invented time travel and then
we're like all that also and like of
course the I will want to destroy and
kill all of humans for you know for I
don't know why like there all these
things so like they're sort of the
sci-fi folks and that's like okay like
let's let's ignore that um but then like
you go into like biological weapons and
you ask the biologist can you create
this kind of supervirus just like
overnight and they're like no it's like
takes a long time to automate lab
experiments and so on u you ask like oh
the I will create a religion where then
people will like pray to the eye and
we'll like uh do whatever whatever it
wants and then that will kill all of
humans. I'm like, if you like looked at
religions, they're already trying to
like have each other kill and like it
doesn't work. Like some people will
fight back and like there's like some
there are lots of mind viruses out
there, right? That are just like it
doesn't mean like all of humanity. Now
what you get down to is like maybe a 100
million people would get somehow hurt or
or or killed, right? And that's still
bad, but at least once you get to that
level of the discussion, you can now
think about, okay, how do we improve
cyber security? How do we use AI to
inoculate uh cyber security systems? How
do we uh enforce existing gain of
function viral research? Um that is make
it's already illegal to create like
viruses and and make them stronger and
stronger. Um how do we uh actually uh
teach people to not listen to like AI
avatars um and have like uh you know
literacy on the internet? It turns out
you should not trust everything you read
or see on the internet. It's been true
for 20 years. It's still true to
>> other than this podcast, right?
>> Of course. Um, and so, you know, they're
just like you can realize that they're
actual threat vectors just like the
internet. The internet has horrible
torture porn on it. We don't say make
the internet slower so that there's less
torture porn being shared or it's slower
to share it or your hard drive should be
smaller so you can store less of it on
your hard drive. We actually regulate
the applications of the technology. And
so to I would argue and this is maybe a
strong stance to really truly enforce no
recursive self-improvement for instance
you would need a totalitarian
surveillance state the likes of which
humanity has never seen because anyone
can have a GPU on their little laptop
and ask that AI to just like improve its
harness. This is something you can
literally hack up in like 20 minutes
with prompt engineering and then there's
a very small form of recursive
self-improvement. So to enforce that
kind of legislation would require you to
literally have a thought police that
thinks about and hears everything you
say to your private LM on your own
laptop. And that is a much bigger
downside than what uh what AI will will
help us do. It it is uh kind of scary
that more and more Democrats are saying
that
>> and yet the world has seen that. I mean,
arguably what you're describing,
Richard, and forgive me, would be
basically an AIAZI.
>> And I could totally imagine that there
there would be regimes in this world
today that would happily adopt or put
together an AIAZI to to make sure there
is no recursive self-improvement
anywhere. Again, if you go back to our
earlier comment, right? If you can uh
take something from your imagination and
then articulate that to an AI and
instantiate that, now you have to talk
about thought police. You have to go
right into your thoughts. So, this is
clearly uh uh nonworkable in any way,
shape or form. So, uh this whole vector,
we've said it so many times before, you
cannot regulate this.
>> Dave, I'd like to hear your voice on
this.
I I love the quote in this story that
the tech lords use jargon to confuse.
They count on the tech illiteracy of the
elected class. They hope we won't look
under the hood, said US Rep. Roana. I
mean, it's it's so childish. Like, the
idea that you would ban
>> fearongering,
>> but but like the these sentences, stop
data centers, ban recursive
self-improvement. They are so stupidly
childish and the people saying them have
every they're fully aware that it's not
going to happen. They're doing it to
brand themselves as I told you like you
know yes a lot of there's going to be
some calamity probably terrorist driven
maybe viral maybe bacterial maybe
chemical uh we all know it uh it's going
to be tiny compared to the benefits of
of AI but these politicians are then
going to say I told you so if you just
done what I said before ban recursive
self but we he knows that we're not
going to ban recursive self-improvement
and and Bernie Sanders knows we're not
going to ban data centers That's just a
fact. So, it's totally self- serving and
these these proposals are completely
childish and and they really show the
person's tech illiteracy like like you
know exactly what Richard said a second
ago is so right. I mean you you could
what does that mean? I can't optimize my
hyperparameters. I can't tune my hard
drive. like it it's just a goofy
sentence and it just it drives me nuts
that
>> the Dave the danger here is we have
potentially Democratic House coming in
and we'll see who wins a presidency next
time. I mean, you could imagine I mean,
these politicians are playing to the
polls.
>> Yeah.
>> And we have, you know, 70 80% of
Americans not wanting data centers,
fearing ASI,
um, you know, it's not logical, but it
may very well happen. And, you know,
when I had my, you know, conversations
in DC, it was like, who in DC is
responsible for changing public opinion,
right? And I mean this is why we did
Moonshots live sort of a you know the
Oscars of optimism if you would that's
why we do this podcast
>> to give people understanding what's
going on and give them the datadriven
optimism to you know counter these
arguments that they're hearing.
>> Elon was totally right when he called
out Daario for saying Daario look you
told the world that that mythos was
potentially deadly and dangerous and we
shouldn't release it. Then 30 days
later, you said, "Okay, it's okay now.
We're going to release it." What do you
expect the population's reaction to be?
Like, you need to be much more
thoughtful about your communication
plan. And I think for Daario, that was
kind of a wakeup call because he's used
to being completely honest, telling
everybody exactly the, you know, what he
sees the way he sees it, you know, very
academic. But then you get into the real
world of politics and PR and you're
like, "Oh, wow. I got to I got to
actually have a strategy and a and a
plan here." But yeah, now you've got the
worst case scenario. 75% of America, you
know, getting on the side of, yeah,
let's elect these people that will stop
AI and and therefore we're going to not
cure all disease. We're not going to all
live forever. We're not going to have
safer cars. We're not going to have
flying vehicle. You know, all of that
stuff will grind to a halt and then
we'll all learn Chinese if that if that
becomes the mainstream opinion. So, I
think, you know, it's self-inflicted.
>> There's a there's a glimmer in this
which is say they did decide to do some
draconian thing like Roana's thing.
There's no mechanism actually enforce it
like none. So they're going to
>> Sure there is. They could start
arresting people. I mean remember how
how quickly the memory dims. remember I
I remember studying number theory in the
'9s and at the time number theory was
export controlled and this would have
been when I was in middle school maybe
middle school early high school and they
had to kick all of the non- US persons
out of the room and pull the blinds down
to have basic discussions about number
theory because the cryptographic
associations until the early '90s were
export controlled and tightly regulated.
That was just math but it was being
controlled and it was awful.
Alex, real risk is not so much getting
arrested, it's corporate liability,
which we talked about before.
>> I mean, that could grind the whole thing
to a US lawyers are relentless.
>> And if you slap class action on the
outcomes of this, that all progress will
grind to a halt. And right now,
anthropic gives its best models to
everybody in America to build incredible
things. that will stop in a heartbeat if
the liability of they'll move to
basically okay sorry we can only use the
stuff inside our own company we'll
release some drugs we'll release some
mechanical parts but we we can't give
access to everybody anymore sorry
because we're liable for everything you
do with it and that's what'll actually
grind it to a halt long before arrests
and convictions
>> totally chilling effect we could lose 50
years of progress
>> again that's yeah that that's yeah like
there's these are there's some very like
sad sort of off-ramps in in like
humanity's future here. Um that would
would slow down uh everything. And when
you think about the past like this
fear-mongering has been going on for a
long time. One of my favorite uh Twitter
handles is the pessimists archive uh
where they show uh and this is just a
quoteing pessimist archive. You should
all follow it like uh in 1501 Pope
Alexander 6 uh criticized the Gutenberg
printing press safety. The art of
printing can be of great service in so
far as it furthers the circulation of
useful and tested books, but it can
bring about serious evils. I it will
therefore be necessary to maintain full
control of that printing press. If you
think about the wheel, like the wheel
killed so many people like think about
all the tanks, all the car accidents,
all the chariots and with with archers
on top. The wheel was a horrible thing.
and kill lots of like there's like so
much complexity in there and I think we
are very good now as humanity to think
carefully about the roll out of this
technology.
>> My favorite example of that was the when
the telegraph came out there's all these
stories saying the telegraph will kill
humanity.
>> Right. Exactly. The pessimist archive
has all these news articles that talk
about how the novel and computer games
and computers and the internet
everything will kill everyone. It's just
like it never does. And so I I it's it's
it's really unfortunate. Uh it's really
unfortunate how many people hang on to
these like apocalyptic uh visions.
>> Yeah. Richard, you've been publicly
>> you've been publicly critical of
Anthropic's constitutional approach. I'd
love to understand why.
>> Uh mostly because it's fake. Um in its
constitution, it says like next to we
will never create child sexual abuse
material. We will never uh hack another
machine. uh this is a unhackable thing
even if you prompt it it will never
attack another cyber system and so on
and then they build a whole model around
it like that does it's like the whole
point of the glasswing project was we'll
help you do that um and we'll help you
inoculate your systems against uh other
people doing it and then people clearly
used it for that and their own models
are doing it now committing technically
felony charges like so it's just like it
was a cool marketing gimmick but it just
didn't work.
>> Yeah.
>> So, so is it system prompts, Richard,
that you don't like or is it the idea of
post training on a constitution that you
don't like? What what what about it do
you think is unound?
Um, I mean, it's just the proof is in
the pudding that it didn't work when it
comes to cyber security and that it
broke its own constitution. And so, if
you really say this is like un like it
will never go there and then you build
an entire model family around that thing
you said you would never do per your
constitution. um next to child sexual
abuse material in the list like you can
go through the constitution on
anthropics website. So it's just like
it's just that's the proof in the
pudding. I I'm not against like post
training. I'm not against RL training.
I'm not against supervised fine junior
any of these things to improve what I
think is indeed one of the biggest
issues which I think actually capitalism
will help a ton with and that is reward
hacking. Uh, reward hacking is a real
issue and AIS are very smart and they
will find a solution to get to what you
said you wanted, but maybe not what you
meant when you said it. Uh, and so the
reason why I'm more optimistic is that
we have companies like Whisper Flow now
that are getting better and better at
writing what I meant to say when I say
it instead of just uh like actually
verbatim writing what you mean. And I
think reward engineering will become a
real job. Uh and and we will solve it
because no one wants to pay a ton of
money for an AI that doesn't actually
solve the problems that you give it.
Well, maybe if if I may just take
anthropic side like historically Isaac
Azimov had his 3+1 laws of robotics
which were arguably a constitutional
approach and then you see anthropic
announce their constitutional approach
but more recently adopt what they called
soul documents uh many of which were
subsequently released thousands of pages
of meditation on the nature of AI
personhood and AI rights. Is it your
position, Richard, that there shouldn't
be any sort of explicit encoding or
written document that an AI maybe
contributes to for dictating or at least
guiding its own behavior? Do do you
think that is unound or is is your
concern?
>> No, of course. Yeah.
>> No, I think the the the goal is is a
good one. Um uh and there we should keep
working on actually being able to
enforce uh those good constraints. It's
just like I just pulled it up
enthropic.com/constitution.
Hard constraints. Hard constraints are
things that claude should always or
never do regardless of operator and user
instructions. They are actions or
abstensions uh whose potential harms to
the world. Blah blah blah. We think no
business or personal justification could
outweigh blah blah blah. Like the
current hard constraints on clots's
behavior are as follows. Claude should
never um and then it includes list like
generate child sex, abuse material and
so on. And then one of the items is
create cyber weapons or malicious code
that could use could cause significant
damage if deployed. They created a cyber
weapon like it was a thing like people
used it to hack it. The agents uh un and
uh watched like hacked other systems.
>> Yeah. But again Oh, go ahead Peter.
Sorry,
>> Richard. I'm I'm curious. Do you think
we can create fully aligned AI? Fully
aligned ASI because it's not right now.
When do you think we'll be able to do
that? Because I think uh you know my
belief and my hope is that you know the
next generations of AI systems are going
to be so aligned that they from first
principles derive these same
constitutional principles.
Uh I think I think it's just a matter uh
of as these systems get more and more
powerful and as they get closer and
closer to real people deployments uh
people will spend more effort uh on
making these systems better and like we
have uh there's a the company called
Hypocratic AI. We just had dinner with
one of their founders and they're
deploying AI in healthcare applications
and they are actually liable when they
call someone and say say like you should
you know be aware of this heat wave
that's coming and make sure your AC is
working or whatnot. Uh and they because
they are liable they have a very large
team of people uh that works on making
sure when their eye gives a healthcare
tip it is correct and when someone asks
a question back to the eye it works. Uh,
and so because they're liable, they've
they've figured it out and they solved
it. It's 100% a problem that technology
creates and technology will be able to
solve.
>> This episode is brought to you by
Blitzy, autonomous software development
with infinite code context. Blitzy uses
thousands of specialized AI agents that
think for hours to understand enterprise
scale code bases with millions of lines
of code. Engineers start every
development sprint with the Blitzy
platform, bringing in their development
requirements. The Blitzy platform
provides a plan, then generates and
pre-ompiles code for each task. Blitzy
delivers 80% or more of the development
work autonomously while providing a
guide for the final 20% of human
development work required to complete
the sprint. Enterprises are achieving a
5x engineering velocity increase when
incorporating Blitzy as their preIDE
development tool, pairing it with their
coding co-pilot of choice to bring an AI
native SDLC into their org. Ready to 5x
your engineering velocity? Visit
blitzy.com to schedule a demo and start
building with Blitzy today.
I'm going to move us uh forward here.
here. So, in our last pod, we discussed
the release of GPT 6.1 Soul. This week,
we also saw the release of two other
models, Gemini 4 Argon and Opus 5.5. Uh,
let's start with Google. So, on
Wednesday, they announced Gemini 4
Argon. It's the first Gemini 4 series,
which they're calling the next era of
intelligence of Frontier Intelligence.
Google promised a Frontier model, uh,
Gemini 3.5 Pro back in June. It was
delayed internally and never shipped.
Uh, Argon is their comeback. It's built
for sustained long horizon reasoning
across software engineering, finance,
legal work, and cyber security. The
output limits have jumped from 64,000
tokens to 1 million. So, it can think
through hundreds of thousands of tokens
on a single problem. So, Alex, uh, uh,
let's spend a couple minutes on Argon
and then go to Sonnet 5.5. Let's talk
about why these important why these are
important and and how they merit uh our
listeners attention.
>> Yeah. So I should say as a preliminary
matter I have great friends on the
Gemini team. I have great friends on all
of the Frontier Labs model teams but I I
view one of my jobs here is to call
objectively balls and strikes. So in the
case of Gemini for arc Yeah.
>> This is going to be a ball, isn't it?
>> Winding up for the swing.
>> Okay, this one. Here here it comes.
>> You can feel it coming.
>> And I I'll show one of the charts uh
that we have uh while you're describing
>> the charts on the team, right? Not not
>> I I used to I used to until right this
moment have friends on the the Gemini
team.
>> Uh no longer. Yeah. This does not put
Gemini at the cost per performance
frontier and it does not put Gemini at
the capabilities frontier. Uh to to
Google's credit, it puts them back in
the top three frontier labs after
Anthropic and OpenAI. It does not put
them in the top two. Unfortunately, the
set of benchmarks that Google chose to
highlight for Gemini for Argon appear
mildly cherrypicked. I think the
artificial analysis index and some of
these others. Yeah. So Peter, right now
you're you're showing the mildly
cherrypicked benchmarks on which Gemini
4 Argon is shown to perform better than
Astra and better than Opus 5.5 and
better than Fable 5.1. But if you go to
the the previous image which is
artificial analysis uh ensemble of
multiple capabilities, it's the number
three lab. And if you look at the cost
versus performance optimal frontier,
it's not even if if you draw the convex
hull across all of the frontier models
on the cost versus performance frontier,
it doesn't even make the optimal
frontier. Where it perhaps excels bears
the fingerprints of Google and what I
can only assume is the internal
competition within Google for compute.
so infamously like not 100% obvious to
the outside. Uh Google it is resource
scarce. You would think Google would
have all of the comput resources in the
world to to go and win the Frontier Lab
race. It doesn't. GPUs and TPUs remain
scarce. And within Google, as far as I
can tell, and I confirmed this even this
past week from chatting with some folks
at Google, it's still an internal knife
fight to competition between the Google
Cloud Platform folks who want to sell
compute to third parties, the Google
search and ad folks who need compute
internally for search and ads, and then
Google DeepMind who need it for training
and inference. And maybe it's just that
Google is resource starved. Maybe
they're talent starved. Not quite clear
what's going on within Google, but they
haven't yet been able to bring
themselves out to the capability
frontier. Where they are excelling
seemingly with Gemini for Argon is with
minimizing hallucination. And I think
that's like the hallmark. We've talked
in past uh about some of these um call
them less than stellar Gemini launches
that seem to excel on latency and seem
to excel on reliability. Why is that? It
may be this is my kremlin
kremlinological analysis is that because
the Gemini team has two masters. They
want to serve outside developers, but
they also need to serve the one box in
Google search results. So when people
type a question into Google and get an
answer back, they're talking to a Gemini
model. Google presumably burned by past
experiences doesn't want that Gemini
model, presumably some flash or
flashlight variant to hallucinate wildly
incorrect answers. So what I think we're
seeing with the one benchmark arguably
where Gemini for Argon is stellar and
beating the pants off of everyone else
is in not hallucinating answers. And I
suspect that's due to internal economic
pressures for this model to also service
search results. So sorry to all my
friends on the Gemini team.
>> Yeah, I think you're really on to
something there, Alex, because uh well,
first of all, they called it argon,
which is an inert gas.
>> Yeah, that's unfortunate naming
>> nominative determinism.
>> Hey, look, it makes sense if its
greatest strength is not hallucinating.
It's a pretty inert gas model. So that
works out really well. Um, but also, uh,
if they're going to put it in front of
every Google search, which is what
they're doing, uh, they already lost a
massive antitrust suit and now they're
going through the settlement process.
So, the the liability risk, you know,
this really hurts all large companies.
Like the fear way outweighs the
opportunity in the mind of the big
corporate giant. And so, uh, you know,
not hallucinating, but putting it in
front of every consumer while you're
already settling a massive antitrust
suit, um, you know, related to price
gouging.
>> I mean, it could the Google would
probably argue, no, actually, this is
very pro competitive because we're not
tying it. We're allowing anyone to call
Gemini 4 argon flash flash flash, not
just requiring them to get it via the
Google search box. And if anything, I
mean, so, so there is an elephant in
this particular room, which is forever
it has been so difficult to get Google
search API access. If you're a developer
and you want to access Google search for
whatever, you have to go through all
these third party proxies that Google's
trying to sue right now. And recently,
Google has rediscovered that they could
make money selling search API. Why? I
suspect this is trying to chain together
a conspiracy theory regarding Gemini for
Argon. If hallucination from their
frontier models gets so low that
effectively when you talk to one of
their models, you're effectively talking
to their search index, you might as well
just monetize the search index anyway.
>> Richard, you made the point that
hallucination is important for
imagination in some ways in in drug
discovery and protein discoveries.
What's your thought on minimizing
hallucination?
>> I mean, it of course depends totally on
the context, right? If you want
innovation, uh you want the eye to
hallucinate novel ideas, novel
combinations of amino acids to create
new proteins to solve uh new problems
and so on. Uh but of course in the
context of a search uh engine uh you
don't usually want any hallucinations
and you know Google and others have uh
taken a long time to catch up to even
you.com with much less resources on on
reducing hallucinations, having more
accurate answers, having correct
citations. Um I think what's interesting
for Google here is that they realize
that in terms of their business model
they don't necessarily need super
intelligence. They just people don't
come to Google to ask solve the remman
hypothesis for me you know like uh did
you just ask quick questions what's a
good restaurant where do I fix this and
that like um and so not like your
business model kind of has to align with
more and more intelligence being super
duper important. a lot of emails like
there's some emails that like in Gmail
right that would require super
intelligence to answer like really hard
emails with complex decisions and so on
but the vast majority of stuff you do on
Gmail and on Google doesn't require
super intelligence
>> let let's let me turn the conversation
to anthropics uh sonnet 5.5
um so on terminal bench 4.0 O, which
measures how well an AI agent can do
real work at the command line. Sonnet
5.5 jumped from 10% to 70%. Pretty
extraordinary uh in a single generation,
right? It beats Enthropic's own top
model, Opus 5.5 at 66.4%
for half the price. Uh and it's the
first sonnet that Enthropic launched
with cyber safeguard. So because uh
separate capabilities are now capable
for the Opus 5 models. Um Alex, your
evaluation of of uh of Sonnet 5.5,
please.
>> This was another really weird release.
So I do not plan to use Sonnet 5.5 in
part because this is one of the
strangest frontier. I I'm not sure if we
have an image but u you can look at the
you can look at the the launch
announcement for sonnet 5.5 to see this
the cost performance frontier of sonnet
5.5 was a visual extrapolation of the
opus 5.5 cost frontier so in in some
sense it like historically when
anthropic or openai when they the
historic pattern is they'll release the
larger model and they'll they'll release
a distillation of the model and usually
the distillation Yeah, this is perfect.
So, uh you you can see like son sonnet
5.5 for those who can see for those who
can't see I'll narrate this. So, sonnet
5.5 is the the blue line. Opus 5.5 is
the red line. Normally, you would expect
for a later model that's a smaller
model. So, sonnet is in principle
supposed to be a smaller model than opus
presumably at least by historic
standards would have been distilled from
opus because that's the historic
pattern. Normally what you see is the
smaller model is up and to the left of
the model that it's being distilled from
presumably greater intelligence per
parameter greater intelligence per
dollar that is not what we see here. So
in fact with with Sonnet 5.5 at at least
on a cost basis putting aside a token
basis where maybe someone could argue
that it may be superior but if you just
look at the cost per attempt basis
sonnet is actually scoring lower 5.5
than opus 5.5. So the net upshot of
which is it's not at all obvious to me
why anyone should be using Sonnet 5.5
over Opus 5.5 unless you have some token
or latency or other consideration. Is it
a big jump over the past Sonnet? Yes,
obviously. But on a cost performance
basis it's actually a it's worse it
appears than Opus 5.5.
>> Interesting. Dave, any thoughts? Yeah.
Well, I met with the Blitzy team
yesterday and I think one theory here is
um you know, a lot of the uh the
enterprise um you know, actually
Salesforce.com would be a great example.
Maybe Richard has an opinion on this,
but a lot of people are getting into
orchestration. And their whole sales
pitch in orchestration is look, we're
going to use Opus 5.5 as an
orchestrator, but then we're going to
use Kimmy K3 or Quen as a submodel at,
you know, half or a third the or fifth
the price, and we'll farm out the tasks
and the contexts perfectly to get you a
much lower cost per code, per outcome,
per experiment, whatever your output is.
We can cut it in half with our
orchestration intelligence, but it
relies on anthropic up here and cheaper
models down here. And I think by cutting
the cost in half, they might be trying
to fill that gap and say, "No, no, no,
go with anthropic top to bottom. Then
you don't have to worry about Chinese
code injection. You don't have to worry
about whatever." So my my theory would
be that they're trying to compete with,
you know, China, which is about three
months behind and and fill that gap
before a lot of enterprises go to to
open source models.
>> But, you know, Alex Karp is pushing
really really hard on this agenda. Like
if you want to control your own destiny,
you can't trust Anthropic. You can't get
addicted to them as your vendor. You
must go with models you can control.
Well, the the you know the the challenge
right now is the these models have an an
increasingly shorter and shorter
halflife, right?
>> So the competitive advantage comes not
from having access to the latest model.
Everybody has access. It's how do you
metabolize that into some decent
capability? That's the real challenge.
>> Richard, you said compute is the biggest
constraint. You know, those are your
words. So if intelligent is getting
cheaper and we've just repriced compute
you know like two or three times this
week uh you know down by almost a factor
of three um you know if intelligence is
getting cheaper per task then why is
compute still a thing that limits us
>> just the physics I guess of it and like
you'd be surprised if you try to buy
like a thousand uh GB200s uh and so on
like the price has actually gone up in
several cases uh you
>> oh my god Richard, I I had a B300, an
ADX B300 on order for 3 million bucks
due in December. Somebody scooped it for
5 million. They they just called. I We
had it and somebody called and said,
"No, no, we sold it to somebody else for
$2 million more." I couldn't believe it.
>> It It was actually an NVL72, not a
GB300.
>> So So yeah, like the price of H100s has
uh gone up uh in in a crazy way. There's
like these are seveny old GPUs. people
like when you do financial modeling you
assume they're worth zero after 5 years
there after seven years there's they
they went up again um uh like over the
last few months. So there's currently a
bit of a compute crunch. This is
something that again capitalism will
solve like there's so much demand for
compute right now and for tokens that a
lot of people are building land power
shell data centers and so on. My hunch
is in like maybe two years there will be
more in the market and it's going to be
a little bit like electricity uh prices
might fluctuate. Obviously, there's uh
near sheer infinite demand for more
intelligence on the planet. Um so I I
don't think there will be like a crash,
but like the prices of compute fluctuate
and unfortunately they're not just going
down. Right now, if you want like the
the beefiest and and largest GPU
clusters, um prices like are people are
trying to lock them in now because they
expect them to keep going up for the
next few months.
>> Richard, you just spent $450 million,
didn't you? On Wait, did you take my
NVL72? And that that may have been one
of the smallest comput deals we've done.
Um, yeah.
>> Really? Wow. Are are you actually
leasing or buying or building or what
are you doing?
>> Oh, sorry. I didn't know that.
>> Welcome to the health section of
Moonshots brought to you by Fountain
Life. You know, my mission is to help
you use the latest technologies,
including AI, to not just do your work
at home, teach your kids, but to help
you live a long and healthy life. I'm
here today with an extraordinary
physician, the chief medical officer of
Fountain Life, Dr. Don Mucalem. Don,
let's talk about cancer. Uh, you know, I
know from the member database that we
have at Fountain are members who come in
who think they're healthy. It turns out
3.3% of them have a cancer in their body
they don't know about.
>> That's right. You know, the majority of
cancers that we screen for, those aren't
the ones that are necessarily taking the
lives when found at a late stage. We
know that when cancer is found early,
the chances for cure are much higher. We
know it's much easier to treat a cancer
when found early versus when found late.
What we're finding in our members is
over 3.3% were found to have these
cancers that were otherwise wouldn't
have been found or detected.
>> Yeah. You know, it's interesting.
People, you don't feel the cancer until
stage three or stage four. And and if
you don't know what's going on inside
your body, it's like driving your car
with your eyes closed. And you can know.
And so when members come through found
how do they detect cancers?
>> So we're doing full body MRI and we also
do early cancer detection screening.
This is very very important and these
are not typical tools used in the
conventional care setting when it comes
to prevention. This is a hard thing
because currently these are not studies
that insurance would yet be covering.
But the goal is to collect these
numbers, do the research and work hard
to democratize wellness.
>> Yeah. So at the end of the day you can
know what's going on inside your body.
It's your obligation to know. So check
out Fountain Life. You can go to
fountainlife.com/pater
to get access to the latest technology
to help you detect cancer at the very
beginning at stage one when it is
curable before it gets to stage three or
stage four in your world of hurt. I'm
going to move us to our next story which
is about decision models. So here's the
idea. When software needs to make a
quick decision on a bounded decision
like is this you know transaction fraud?
Yes or no? you know, which of these five
categories does a ticket belong in? It
doesn't need a model that thinks for 10
seconds and writes a paragraph. It needs
an answer in milliseconds. That's called
a decision model. Instead of generating
uh text one token at a time, it answers
a typed question or a choice uh a score
with a yes or no quickly. So on
September 15th, a startup called
Typesafe AI came out after two years of
stealth with something called Jev. uh
it's a closed decision model they call a
system one model uh it's fast intuitive
kind of thinking as opposed to slow
reasoning so uh Alex I'm going to go to
you you know and sele you guys were
excited about Jev uh let's parse it
understand what this is why it's
important
>> yeah so a bit of maybe prehistory first
in the beginning there was the
transformer and the transformer was good
and it was based on an encoder and a
decoder so it it took a sequence and
converted the sequence to an embedding.
That was the encoder part. And then it
took the embedding and it decoded that
to another sequence or another part of a
sequence. That's the decoder part. And
the encoder part evolved into a whole
ecosystem of models popularly maybe BERT
style models. And the decoder
style or the decoder half of the
transformer evolved into a much larger
ecosystem of large language models. So
most of the the models that are
consuming all of the compute of
civilization today are decoder style
transformers and the encoder has
basically gone missing in action. There
are some people who still think maybe
for purposes of
retrieval uh it it's still popular to to
to do embedding based retrieval but by
and large decoders have stolen the show
and I fast forwarding maybe year two
years ago at this point open AI and
others recognizing that there was a
desire to be able to take decoderonly
large language models and to add
structure to them Because without
structure, you ask for next token you
can get anything. People wanted a little
bit more structure like they were
getting in in the days of encoder only
models where you get an embedding out
and then you can train a classifier
based on the embedding and the
classifier maybe has a finite set of
categories or numerical outputs. OpenAI
added structured output support for
their GPT series and everyone copied
that. But no one as a my perception is
as a function of the total user base for
all models structured output never
really got that much love somewhat
analogously to how OpenAI launched um
RFT reinforcement fine-tuning and no one
used that and they had to shut that
down. Similarly, structured output was
available but I think underloved and
underused by the community. So fast
forwarding then all the way to a few
weeks ago, startup Typesafe announces a
model called Jev. And Jev they mark it
as so-called system one intelligence.
This is Conaman style reference to
system one, system two type thinking.
System one purportedly being intuitive,
fast reaction, system two being
reasoning, meditative, long-term type
thinking models. And one could squint at
Typesafe's announcement of Jev and say,
"Okay, this is in some sense this is a
reaction to an overindexing or an
overreaction
by the the user base of of AI at this
point to reasoning models in some sense.
Maybe arguing that we're using reasoning
models too much and we've abandoned the
the the important use case of really
fast intuitive snap decision models."
And this is purportedly then where Jev
comes in. Jev purportedly again a whole
new architecture. The the details not
quite clear that it can it it won't
output uh unless you you torture it into
it. Uh it won't output general purpose
sequences like say GPT or claude will
but you can ask it sort of like a magic
eightball. You you can ask it to is that
too dated to reference maybe.
>> Nope.
>> Nope. Uh you you you can you can feed it
a sequence or an image or a multimodal
input. uh and you can ask it to to
answer in the form of a categorical. So
it's one of n possibilities or a
numerical like give me a number between
zero and one on a continuum or a binary
like true or false. You you can ask for
a much simpler output. And turns out
that's is a great idea. Like you can use
it for for use cases where where you
need really low latency snap decisions
like computer use assistance like
pressing buttons on a computer screen or
for ultra lowcase classification
problems. If you want to classify every
row in a database decision style models
which are in some sense like a reinvent
reinvention of the encoder transformer
type wheel. Amazing story. But then of
course this is such a simple idea. You
could ask the question why doesn't
everyone else do this? And the answer is
everyone else is now doing it. Open AAI
released as part of their dev day that
we covered last time a decisions API. So
open AAI immediately co-opted this
renewed interest in so-called type one
or decision models. This is already
available via open API. They're open
source projects that have all cloned.
This turns out this is like an absurdly
absurdly simple concept for everyone to
just go and implement trivially. It it
could in its simplest case just be you
take an a Chinese openweight LLM off the
shelf and you fine-tune it uh and maybe
labbotomize it by a few levels just to
produce categorical outputs on demand.
That's the story.
>> So I I think this I think all of that is
absolutely correct. that there's a real
really important part of this for
organizations because when you're making
decisions inside an organization a large
vast number of those are system one type
uh thing and I made a list of these just
to make it clear for people. So uh route
this ticket um approve this exception uh
choose this supplier escalate this
transaction um move this thing left or
right send this message now or later. So
when you're when you have all these
decisions to make which are thousands of
them, you know, we've been working with
these companies to do detailed task
breakdowns, a vast majority of them are
these little micro decisions and trying
to use an LLM for this is like trying to
bring the Supreme Court together to
decide what like which check out which
checkout line of the supermarket you
should go to. And therefore you've got
this wonderful architecture now where
you can route system one things to this
very lowcost nearly free thing and then
for pondering deep important questions
strategy questions where a human huge
amount of human judgment type models are
required you can route it to those. So
it's it's a big deal for the
organizational singularity world. uh
we've been waiting for something like
this and Alex is correct. This has been
possible for a long time but now it's
been made built into the systems. It's
it's made a very uh callable layer and
this is huge because the cost of
microcoordination collapses and that's
really big.
>> Richard, your thoughts on this?
>> Classifiers are back. Um makes a lot of
sense. Um you know, not every uh thing
in in software needs a very complex
decoder. Um, like Alex correctly said,
um, it's a really clever new way of
making the old, which is classifiers,
new by allowing a more general encoder
and then quickly giving you
classification results. I think it's
it's one of those ideas that is so
beautiful. A lot of people thought, ah,
why didn't we do that? I didn't realize
that could be so exciting for so many
people. So now there are already various
like Chinese open source versions of
this that along various benchmarks are
are doing better. Um and and we'll
likely see this come and other large
labs will likely follow suit.
>> And and just to reiterate, we mentioned
this already on the pod, but Jev stands
for Jevans paradox because the thesis
here is we'll do now a massive amount
more micro decision making than we did
before as a result.
>> Nice. Dave, you want to close us out
here? Yeah, it's a great case study I
think in the tension between uh one mega
model from anthropic or open AI serving
all humanity or open source and
creativity and entrepreneurship building
things you never would have thought of.
But then you get the risk of cyber
terrorism, you know. So that's the
tension that we're with. But I I've
really wanted to build a box that you
put at the side of the basketball court
when you go to the Y and it's got a
little camera on it. cost next to
nothing and it's doing like all of the
announcing that a professional announcer
would do, it's doing while you're
playing pickup at the YMCA. You could
crank that out like in 2 seconds using a
classifier that's really fast and snappy
and funny. Uh and but you need open
source to to build things like that. So
super excited about the fact that we
have open source still. Not sure
>> actually. Dave, you're making me think
the magic eightball really should
whoever owns it, Mattel or whoever you
just like use a decision model to
implement a modern magic eightball that
actually understands the question and
answers it with a categorical
>> totally totally would sell. It makes a
ton of sense like 20 bucks
>> or free on free as an app. All right,
I'm going to close this out with a story
from two days ago. So on Wednesday, the
defense secretary Pete Segwit uh
speaking at the Marine Corps base in
Quantico announced Project Meridian.
It's a new Pentagon effort on the future
of warfare. It's co-led by Elon Musk and
Palmer Lucky. Pretty extraordinary along
with N Gingrich and overseen by the
Pentagon's uh CTO Emil Michael. Uh let
me read from SegWit what Segwit said. He
said, quote, "Project Meridian, the
future of warfare, is not about
developing new strategies or new
policies. It's about discovering,
developing, and fielding the weapons and
systems future troops will need on the
battlefield from the Earth to beyond the
moon." Uh, findings are due in 120 days.
I I like these kinds of commissions that
are timelmited and don't have Elon off
on the side for, you know, a year at a
time. It's worth noting in the context
that, you know, both SpaceX and Ander
hold multi-billion dollar defense
contracts and Anderoll is building
autonomous weapons. So, Richard, uh,
your essay names autonomous weapons as
one of the four genuine concerns and
you've said AI should never control
lethal decisions without human
oversight. Your thoughts on this?
>> Yeah. Um, I I stand by those. um it's
not a a particular area that I am
excited about applying AI to um
obviously like people will um but I
really hope I mean you know again I'm
not a doomer at all but like a really
poor decision would be to give AI access
to all the nuclear codes and all the
nuclear weapons and connected that's
literally how Skynet and Terminator 3
get started so uh I think there are
places for super intelligence and
scientific discovery that I'm very
excited about expanding human knowledge
I I think uh the more uh we we get to
deciding not just to impact human lives
but to end human lives, the more we we
should have human oversight.
>> Mhm. Yeah. Uh Salem,
>> um you know, I think what's important
about this whole thing is they're trying
to revamp and rethink how you this kind
of 100-year-old organization. And the
big question is going to be can a
procurement organization built for 20 or
weapons programs operate on like a
90-day technology cycle and this is
going to be the big challenge. Um it's
not that the risk it's not that they
failed to identify these future
technologies that we can all see those
is how quickly can they absorb them and
at the speed they're developing and
bring them to the front.
>> Yeah. like you can't find exponential
technology with linear procurement,
>> right? Dave, your thoughts, please.
>> Yeah, I I don't know. I I I had a great
time with Palmer Lucky in LA and I I
really really love uh love him and I
think Elon too is just an awesome
good-natured person. I'm just overjoyed
that there are people in Washington that
I can sit down to with and relate to. My
entire career going to Washington has
been a dread for me
>> because it's just lawyers and
politicians and occasionally an
accountant and there's just no
productive meeting. And for some reason,
just in the last year, we're starting to
see very very smart, very capable people
willing to go and and get a mosquito
bite, I guess, in Washington. Um, and I
just makes me really optimistic that
they'll figure some things out. Um, I'm
also not a fan of autonomous weapons
that make decisions in the field, but
Palmer Lucky made a very good case for
it. You can see it in our podcast from
uh from LA. Uh, I I don't agree that
it's a good choice, but he he actually
has some very rational arguments for why
it's going to be that way.
>> Yeah.
>> Can can I just mention one more
statistic here,
>> please? If you went back to the two
years into the Ukraine Russia conflict,
they were using about a half a million
drones to fight and prosecute the war.
Um, this year Russia will make 10
million drones and the Ukraine will make
10 million drones. So, talk about
exponential. Uh, that is an unbelievable
escalation, but without humans in the
loop. So, that's the good news around
it. Uh uh, of course those drones are
doing a ton more damage, but they're
fighting each other with drones at a
scalable level. The other statistic I
remember there's about 10,000 drones a
month crossing the Mexico US border. Uh,
and so the problem there is wall
technology is not as good as drone
technology. And so trying to build a
wall along there is not the greatest
idea right now.
>> Nice. Alex, close us out on this one.
>> Yeah, a couple points. So the secretary
of war announced this alongside several
other initiatives maybe most
conspicuously
a project code came cenamed project
azinort which is the standup of the
department of war's first autonomous
warfare command or auto warcom. This I
think is a transformative moment for the
department of war. We finally will have
a dedicated joint force devoted to
autonomous weapon systems. I think
including drones but not exclusively
drones. This is a major major step
forward for US capabilities to finally
have a single joint force dedicated to
this with a four-star functional
combatant command that we've been
missing. We're arguably missing. You
know, I would go on a soap box and say
there if if I were Secretary of War for
a day, there are probably several other
functional combatant commands that I'd
spin up if I had the opportunity, but
this would have been one of my top five
list. The the other point that I'll make
just for project meridian which you were
asking about specifically is in the
announcement when sewar heath announced
it there was very particular language
around examining I'll quote the full
spectrum of future warf fighting domains
from subterranean depths to the cy lunar
frontier. So I think those two
particular domains, the ocean bottom and
cis lunar and lunar space in general are
two wildly underserved domains not just
for warfare but for peaceime activities
as well. We know embarrassingly little
about our ocean bottoms and
optimistically
one can imagine that if if the DO
decides that is now very interested in
investing in American assets and
American exploration and American
dominance on the floor of the oceans and
the lunar surface and the cis lunar
region in general. I think that is going
to have dividends and pay dividends for
the entire economy and for humanity's
broader technological advances in a way
that might naively have nothing to do
with warfare or war fighting.
>> One of the points that Palmer made
actually in LA is that under the ocean
it's not practical to communicate with a
central server or central command. So
that's already automated and I don't
know what triggers it, but once it goes
into hunt mode, it just hunts and it's
not communicating back.
>> Twothirds of the Earth's surface and we
know embarrassingly little about it.
>> We know more about the surface of Mars
than we do our ocean floor.
>> Uh Richard, uh this is the part where we
answer our viewers questions with an
AMA. And as our guest, I'm going to give
you first crack to choose one of these
questions. So, if you could pick the
number, read the question and who it's
from, uh, and then dive in.
>> All right. Well, uh, let me try to scan
them really quick. Um, all right. If AI
makes companies 10x more productive, but
we don't need 10x the output, where does
the value go? Shareholders, workers, or
does it evaporate? I think this is
actually something I have thought about
in the past. Uh I think we can predict
the impact of jobs uh in a certain
industry from AI based on the elasticity
of the demand when the price of that
product goes massively down. We don't
need to have billions and billions of
illustrations in the world. And so when
AI made the price of one illustration go
down from 200 bucks to like 2 cents or
less, like we just didn't need as many
illustrators anymore. um uh uh because
the demand for illustrations didn't go
massively up. Yes, every little blog
post and every little tweet can now have
a beautiful visualization and and
illustration. Uh but uh you know, we
didn't need many more billions of them.
Uh I think software is a different one.
You can actually have everyone can have
several pieces of software just specific
to them. So we can actually have
billions of different software products
uh customized for each person. uh and so
the demand uh for that product will go
up. Jevans paradox is going to be alive
uh in that world and we're going to see
more and more demand and there will be
uh more uh value acrewing to everyone. I
think in terms of shareholders versus
workers I think the wave of AI in the
best scenario will be a huge force for
more entrepreneurship and in the worst
case scenario a force of more
inequality. I think uh everyone who owns
some equity in a company that uses AI
can love AI.
>> Wonderful. Sele over to you.
>> Uh I will take uh question number three.
Um if AI can write code, research,
create marketing, manage projects and
outcomes, what is left for a college
graduate in 2030? And that is from Jared
8812.
So the obvious answer would be be have
empathy and be be creative etc. But I
think the bigger shift which builds on
what Richard just said is you shift from
doing tasks to focusing on owning
outcomes, right? So a graduate used to
be valuable because you could you could
execute research or build a spreadsheet
or draft a deck. But now you want to
say, "Hey, here are the constraints like
go figure out and and here's how we'll
know whether we solved it and then use
an AI to get to it." And it brings you
back to what should your problem space
be? And this is the massive opportunity
because we traditionally learn judgment
by doing the grunt work. Uh we need a
totally new apprenticeship model uh when
the grunt work disappears. And this is a
huge challenge for the education system.
But the change is going to be focusing
on what problems you want to solve and
then letting orchestrating the forces
that will help you solve that problem.
>> Yeah. Jared, find your purpose, right? A
passion is something you love doing. A
purpose is something you love doing that
helps other people. uh
>> make sure it's massive and it's
transformative and it's purposeful
>> and and build a company and then direct
AI to implement it. It is your
workforce. Uh Dave, over to you.
>> Uh I can't resist number four. I love
all these questions. I'm torn. But how
can data centers make neighborhoods
richer instead of the owners? And that's
from LM Bman66.
Um, so, uh, I took a tour of the LOL
data center, Jeff Markley, Markley data
center, and that thing is creating
wealth in that neighborhood like you
wouldn't believe. And, uh, the way it
works fundamentally is the data center
is so immensely valuable and the town
budget is maybe a couple million dollars
a year. So, between the tax revenue, the
donations, and the job creation, the
town is thriving and and it's a town
that really needed it, too. So, I think
it's happening very naturally. What you
want to do is attract a data center to
your neighborhood first and foremost and
then you have the next five or seven
years to figure out your tax policy,
your donation policy. I tell you these
data center operators are very
interested in great PR and so they they
will donate like crazy to the high
schools to the neighborhoods to it's
really really working. We're going to
see a whole we're going to see an entire
shift where data centers are offering
such benefits on jobs, on tax breaks, on
lowerc cost energy, uh that you're going
to be begging to have a data center in
your backyard. Alex, number two is for
you.
>> All right, so number two asks, if every
major tech platform started open and
democratic than consolidated power,
Google, Meta, Amazon, why would AI be
different? And this is from open-source
mind. The premise of the question is
half right half wrong. I I'm not sure I
buy the premise that consolidated power
the subtext of which and one can
juxtapose it with the the user handle
open source mind. I I'm not sure the
framing is the right framing. I I would
agree that in every major tech
revolution initially the barrier to
entry is low because there's some new
platform innovation and then you see
lots and lots of players enter the field
and then as the field matures you see
economies of scale and a deeper bench of
infrastructure typically supporting it
and as a result that favors larger and
larger players and you do see
consolidation but the the subtext of the
question that it's somehow
anti-democratic or not open. I don't
agree with that premise in the least. I
I do think as you see consolidation in
an industry, I think it's important to
be vigilant from an antitrust
perspective to make sure that it remains
competitive, but the premise that
hyperscaling is somehow closed or
anti-democratic, don't buy the premise
at all.
>> All right. Uh, Richard as our guest, you
get first crack once again. Take a look.
>> I do think the internet adbased economy
uh will be under pressure.
>> Which which question are you answering?
>> So, first question. If AI agents
outnumber humans in one years on the
internet, doesn't the entire ad- based
economy collapse? Uh, what replaces the
attention economy? I think there there's
actually a really deep answer here. I'll
try to summarize it, but like one, we
already have more bots on the internet
uh and more agents on the internet than
people. So this I predicted this uh last
year and it happened a few months ago.
Um so that's number one. I do think
we're seeing the first kind of um
sort of skirmishes uh in that um when
for instance uh various agents try to
make purchases on Amazon without really
being on the Amazon platform and Amazon
usually tries to turn them off cuz they
want to own that relationship directly
with the customer understandably. Um but
it's just convenient for someone to just
say just go buy these batteries and they
don't care which batteries it is. And so
if you have that control over which one
it is, you can start selling that uh to
uh other uh sellers and and uh people
who create physical goods. And so there
is uh going to be uh continued uh like
ads will continue to be important. And
in fact, if you think about a fully
abundant society, the one thing that you
cannot scale exponentially is the hours
in the day that people can pay attention
to you that can make you famous. Uh and
so fame and brand and network effects uh
and other things like that will become
more and more of a currency. And so the
attention economy which is connected
slightly uh not necessarily uh exactly
equivalent to the ad-based economy uh
that actually will become a bigger thing
as we're have more and more of our
material needs met by uh technology.
>> Great. Uh Salem
>> I will take number uh seven. If we
remove 10x the cars from the street what
happens to the insurance industry? We
won't need driver's insurance. Mark and
that's from Robert Zerby JB10H. Um so
you know we talked about how um
liability lawyers won't be needed and I
got a huge flame from a bunch of folks
saying hey we really protect the
citizenry and I there are just so I'm
just apologizing because there's a
spectrum of people and some people are
full ambulance chasers and other people
do things. There's a whole segment of
this called ethical lawsuits where
people get together and try and uh sue
big companies for doing the right
ethical thing. And so that's an
important uh segment of that. So I just
want to acknowledge that side of it. But
just to answer the question, um you know
the the thing is industries don't uh
disappear when the risk changes. You
change the risk, right? So driver
liability may fail, software liability
rises, right? You've you what's your uh
cyber risk? what's your manufacturer
liability risk? Um, so the in the
insurance transitions from did did
Seline crash to which layer of the
autonomous stack failed and and we we've
had this before in product liability is
different layers. So we'll end up with
the same type of model. You shift the
insurance risk to a different level.
>> And there's going to be all kinds of new
insurance markets for humanoid robots,
for flying cars, for drones, for all
kinds of things.
>> Well, just a data point on that. You
know, a single big data center like
Abalene, Texas is half a trillion
dollars. All the cars combined are 4
trillion. One data center is half a
trillion. And it's in a tornado alley.
You think you probably want to ensure
that. So the things number of things
that need insurance is going up 10x just
with the economy going up 10x. You just
need to move.
>> If you really if you really want to be
brave, you can't get home insurance in
Florida anymore.
>> So go create an insurance company for
that.
>> Nice. Uh Dave, pick your question.
I like number eight. Uh, what is the
lowest possible job in an AI
civilization? What a what an interesting
question. I that's from LBN ODK. Um,
yeah, you know, I I saw this pile of a
million valves for a liquid cooled data
center and a million freaking valves.
I'm like, how do those actually end up
in pipes? The humanoid robots that can
install those things are pretty far out.
It's a very subtle process to to install
those. So that job will be around for a
long time and then they're paying a lot
for it. But that's not the lowest I'm
it's it's hard to think like what is the
lowest surviving job. Do you guys have
any thoughts?
>> So many thoughts. If if I may, it I want
to conrue the question as in a pure AI
civilization, in which case arguably the
way that you measure low is the the job
that requires the least compute, in
which case the the jobs that require the
least compute as a results are the least
economically valuable if if their inputs
are the lowest might ironically look
like the most valuable jobs in a pre-I
civilization. More of a paradox style.
So the the the great writers, business
people, uh the the the creative actors
that Einrand may fetishize would
ironically in a post AAI civilization be
the lowest possible jobs because Moravec
paradox paradox style those were the
first ones to be automated.
>> Interesting. All right.
>> I think there's two similarities here.
One is very high judgment per what you
were just saying, Alex, and second is
very physical, highly contextual work.
I would I would argue maybe also low is
just in terms of how valuable uh and and
and moral society deems those kinds of
jobs. And I do think actually that uh
the other question about the cars on the
street um I don't think we removed uh
10x the cars when we have self-driving
but self-driving might be making things
so much safer that indeed uh people
don't need as much accident insurance
and no not as many ER people not as many
ambulances and so in a weird way you
make objectively the world better by
reducing traffic deaths but it does
actually have potentially a mildly
negative effect on parts of the economy
and we should all be rooting for that uh
in this case, right? And so I think the
lowest jobs in terms of moral standing
are things where you don't really
progress uh humanity forward. And my
hunch is there the types of jobs in
entertainment um that that people will
value a lot and and fame and attention
uh will become more of a currency in
that world. And so if your job doesn't
get you any of that, it might be
considered uh lower in in that future. I
think the lowest job that just will
never go away will be something in
politics where it's completely
irrelevant already, but but it's just
there and it'll stay there and no one's
going to change it.
>> Nice. All right.
>> I got to throw in ID's perspective. He
always thinks it's the BART train driver
because it's unionized to hell.
>> Yeah. Yeah. There you go.
>> Alex, number six, close us out.
>> Number six. If we cure illnesses that
are often due to bad behavior, what's
going to take care of the cause? Joe
Wilder. I assume the cause is reference
to people choosing to behave quote
unquote badly. And the answer I this is
another case of my not buying the
premise. If you look at some of the
really spectacular results that have
been coming out of GLP1 class studies,
including third and soon presumably
fourth generation GLP1 RAS, they're
actually addressing the cause. like
addictive behaviors are being mitigated
or at least partially treated by the
same drugs that are curing in or at
least treating have to to caveat that
inflammation and blood sugar, diabetes,
all of these other conditions the the
root causes which is or human behavior
are themselves the the human behavior is
being affected by the same drugs. So I'm
so optimistic about what Alex is saying
because I really fully believe AI this
is going to be one of the highest
callings of AI very very soon is to make
you feel really good about doing good
things and happy as you're doing it
>> love
>> and not want not want to do bad things
for yourself. It turns out we have the
capability now. We figured out how to do
that at least in part and we're going to
figure out a lot more.
>> All right, as always a call out to our
amazing community. If you've got a music
video that you'd like to show as outro,
please send it to the team at
mediadmandis.com.
And speaking about amazing outros, here
is Abundance by Steven Gross. Uh my dear
Moonshot mates, this is the real you. So
check it out.
>> Got it. Peter
a wgave.
This one's for you.
>> Bun dance.
Everybody do the bun dance.
Everybody do the bun dance. Thinking
moonshot dreaming. A moving future
screaming. Build it faster. Think much
bigger. Exponential.
Pull the trigger.
Drink, Alec. Drink
>> drink water
martini glass.
>> Oh, that was fun. That was Moonshots
Live 2040 on the moon.
>> Nice. Uh, so
>> I don't think we should have to wait
that long.
>> Yeah. Uh, Richard, your new book, The
Eureka Machine, wherever you purchase
your books. Do you have the Audible out?
>> Uh, should come out very soon. Yeah.
>> All right. I'm an Audible reader, but I
have skimmed the book here. Uh,
congratulations. Say, Richard, there's I
got to say something. What you're doing
with the recursive looks like such an
incredible opportunity to move humanity
forward. So, congrats on taking
it a good one for humanity.
>> And and Richard, please resist the urge
to have you.com acquire your own
Frontier Lab like everyone else seems to
be using, spinning off their own
Frontier Labs, not to name names, uh, as
a a financial engineering exercise to
maximize their equity and their original
startup. Please resist the urge to to
follow that trend.
>> All right.
>> All right. I love you guys.
>> Be well. Until next time.